Welcome again and last lecture we talked
about some properties of Perspective
Projection so I'm gonna continue with this
team today and try to derive a few more
interesting properties. So last time we
studied that parallel lines can merge to a
vanishing point. Today, we're gonna take
up the next property that are listed then
which is that nearer objects are lower in
the image. As you see here, by considering
the polls and the bottoms of this polls in
this diagram. How do we go about proving
this? That's the question. So let's start
by noting that all of these objects are on
a ground plane. So, on a ground plane the
following is true, the y coordinate in the
wall satisfies the condition that y= -h.
So, think of h as the height of the camera
or the person taking the picture. So if
the equation of the ground plane is y =
-h, then any point in the ground plane is
gonna have project to a y coordinate which
is y = -fh over z. So that's just from the
equation of Perspective Projection. So,
can we derive anything further? So, let's
just follow this through. So, suppose we
consider. Z going to infinity, so we're
considering follow a point. What will
happen to y? So y will go to zero. So,
okay, And now we can consider points which
are closer to us. So if there are points
which are nearer to us. What will happen?
We'll have y will be more negative. So
what does that mean? That means that it
will be lower in the image, So if we
consider the points here, These and so
forth. So we, we have points associated
with depths z1, z2, z3 and obviously z3 is
greater than z2 which is greater than z1.
And the associated y coordinates, they are
all negative And the y coordinate for the
point one is the most negative,
intermediate are the least negative. So in
other words, we see that nearer points are
going to be lower in the image plane.
Okay, here's another obvious kind of
statement but we want to prove it using
our techniques that nearer objects look
bigger. So what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
take up one of these, these, these poles.
A nd I'm gonna derive what it's length is
in the image. So its length in the wall is
going to be n. So, that's the height of
the object out in the wall. In the image,
we are going to consider the point
corresponding to its bottom and its bottom
is that x, -h, z. So where does the -h
arise from? This is the height of the
camera. Okay, so what's the top of the
point going to be? So let's consider this
location. So, it's the same x-coordinate,
the same z-coordinate but the y-coordinate
is different and it's larger by l. So, l
is the height, L is the height of the
object so this height is l. So, that gives
us the following equation for the top of
the object. And now, things are pretty
straight forward. We just have to derive
what the bottom projects to. So, what is
the bottom projector? It's gonna project
to fx upon z, -fh upon z. And what does
the top projector, Fx up on z, Fl-h upon
z. So, If I consider The difference
between this. What is that? That's
essentially fl upon z. And that you can
think of is the vertical size of the image
in the projection. And clearly they have
the property here that large Z Means That
This is smaller. So, in a similar way we
can prove whereas the properties that true
of an image created by Perspective
Projection. So, it's all quite straight
forward. You just have to apply these
rules, fx up on z, fy up on z and just try
to figure out what are the appropriate
choices of x, y, and z to plug in to these
formulas. Let's try to get some more
infusion. But before we do that, I want
you to have in mind the physical model
which are waves in motion. And I have
shown that here. So, imagine here that
there is a person who is standing there
looking at some object. This is the object
in the wall and what we do is we have a
pinhole, so this is going to be the
equivalent of the pinhole. But instead of
having the image plane which is at f
behind the pinhole, we imagine a virtual
image plane which is f in front of the
pinhole. So, it's just the, considering
the same f but we are putting it in front
rat her than in the back as we had
earlier, instead of what we had earlier.
Okay, what [inaudible] going to do this?
So essentially, you can imagine that you
have a transfer in sheet, so you have a
transfer in piece of glass which you put
at a distance of f in front of the
pinhole. So, the image is clear to as
follows. And again the similar triangle
reasoning will go through and we will be
able to derive the projection equations, x
= fx upon z, y is fy upon z. And now
What's cool about this is that you got
through the other mind of signs. So In my
last picture, I talked about getting
either minus signs and software or just
inverting the image top down and left to
right. Here, you can think of this is a
physical model which you can keep in your
head as a way in which perspective
projection happens with no sign inversion.
So, one way to think about is that this is
how an artist operates. An artist is
trying to paint a picture of an external
world on an easel. So, this is going to be
a kind of the artist's easel. On which he
or she is trying to paint this picture of
a tree outside. And they want the, the
picture to be such that a person situated
at the right location would get exactly
the same set of rays from the painting as.
He or she would get from the real world
and then obviously they would, they would
imagine the construction like one I've
shown here. So, what this makes very clear
is that, what's very important is the
location of the pinhole sometimes we will
call this the center of projection Because
all the rays which form the image go
through the center of projection. And
Perspective Projection is really a mapping
from points in three-dimensional-space,
xyz to this collection of rays and what's
the collection of rays we are talking
about? All the rays which go through the
center of projection and that abbreviated
sometimes as COP. So this is the
fundamental way to think about it, what,
once you see it this way, you realize that
the projection surface. The projection
surface that we considered here, it is not
very important. I mean, we can put it, put
a plane there, we could put a sphere so
you could imagine that you have a
transparent globe and the center of that
globe is the pinhole or whatever smooth
surface you like. It doesn't matter. We
just need some way of recording the
intersection of rays on to a surface. So,
this shows up some kind of discussions
when people are confused that when in, in
human perception, images are created in
the retina and the retina is not flat and
it's not exactly spherical. It doesn't
matter, All you need is a way to record in
a one to one fashion the set of rays going
through the pinhole. And each ray
corresponding to a set of points of the
three-dimensional-space. Thinking of it
this way also makes some other intrusions
more evident. What's the right way to
measure image size? So, we could think
about different ways of doing it. You
could measure image size and pixels. You
could measure it in microns and the image
sensor. But, let me argue to you that the
right way to measure image size is visual
angle so I've shown that in this diagram.
So, we have some object out in the wall,
and it creates a certain image. But what I
can do is to measure the length of this
image with this visual angle theta and
this is the visual angle subtended at the
center projection. How do we measure this
theta in a standard way? By radiance or
degrees or whatever. So, this is a major
of, a natural major image size. And once
you have this major image size, you can of
course always convert this into size on
the, on the image plane because we're
going to have a simple relationship. So,
theta is equal to sum l upon f, where f is
the, the distance Between center of
projection and the image plane. So, but
measuring the size of an object on the
image plane in degrees therefore is a very
natural thing. So, we do this all the time
when we talk about field of e view of
cameras of the field of view of the human
visual system. We always describe that in
terms of degrees. We don't measure it out
in terms of megapixels o r number of cons
and so on. Degrees is, subtended at the
center of projection is the natural unit.
I'll give you some examples of what one
can do once you realize that this is the
natural unit. We can. We can calculate for
some common objects on what size the
subtend on the on the [inaudible]. So
let's take the example of the human head.
So the average human head is nine inches
high. So, suppose that we are looking at a
person who is nine feet away. So, then,
what you're going to get is angle theta is
gonna be one upon twelve because there are
twelve inches in a foot, So this one upon
twelve is in radiance of course so that
corresponds to 4.8 degrees. So, if the
person was at eighteen feet what would we
get? You would get. That the head
[inaudible] 2.4 degrees. So, note that
this gives you a way of measuring distance
because let's assume that all human heads
are roughly the same. So, the beam has
access to the, the size subtended on the
retina. So is it, if, if the size is 2.5
degrees you can say I'm looking at a
person who is eighteen feet away. So, this
is quite convenient. Let me conclude my
discussion of perspective by trying to
capture the big story which I think can be
summarized in two main principles. First
principle is that objects which are part
of it looks smaller. Looks smaller meaning
that the angles up tended on the image
plane is smaller. And the basic factor is
the scaling factor of one over z. So when
z is larger, you'll gonna get a smaller
projection on the image. So we have
studied this in great detail already. The
second effect which I wanna point out is
that for sharpening. Objects that are
slanted with respect to the line of sight
project to smaller sizes on the image
plane. And this killing factor here is
Cosine Sigma. So let me define sigma. So
sigma here is, is shown in this figure. So
we have the line of sight from the eye and
then we have the surface normal. The
surface normal to the surface which I have
shown here in blue And sigma is the angle
between the two. So, if a surface is dir
ectly in front of us, sigma will be zero.
If the surface is completely edged on,
then sigma will be 90 degrees. So, sigma
is the angle between the line of sight and
the surface normal. And sometimes we call
sigma, the surface slant. And, essentially
this is gonna cause a further diminishing
in size by a factor of cosine sigma. We
can get into this in more mathematically
precise in a more mathematically precise
way later. But, I think you can get this
notion quite intuitively. So, these are
the two main effects of perspective
projection, this [inaudible] effect and a
[inaudible] effect. This is why if we have
a circle in the wall, it will typically
project to an ellipse and the ratio of the
major to minor axis is going to be related
to how the circular disk is arrayed with
respect to the line of sight. Finally, I
want to conclude by talking about an
approximation to Perspective Projection
called Orthographic Projection and we use
this quite a lot. And the reason is that
it makes the mathematics much simpler at
in certain times. When is this
approximation valid? This is an
approximation to perspective and you're
looking at an object which doesn't have
that much depth variation inside it and is
relatively following. So imagine that here
is the, the camera indicated by the eye
and you're looking at some object and this
distance might be like twenty feet or
something like that. And, the depth
variation within the object is more like
one foot. So that's the kind of scenario.
You're looking at some smallish object
relative to the distance that it is with
respect to the camera. So, what happens
there? Let's derive some equations here.
So essentially, the perspective effect is
going to give me that x = fx up on Z1 And
x2 is fx2 up on z2, Okay. Now, what we can
do is to assume that this f up on z1 and f
up on z2 are approximately the same. So,
if f up on z1 approximately, f up on z2.
In which case we can then say x1 is sum
alpha times x1. And x2 is alpha * x2.
Okay. So, this of course is the So, this
is image, it's the im age quantities. So,
what we have here is just scaling. So, a
scaling of, of the x-coordinate. And what
we'll we do for the y-coordinate? It's
gonna be [inaudible] of the y1 is alpha
times. Y1 and y2 is alpha * y2. So, when
can we make this assumption that f up on
z1 is roughly the same as f up on z2.
It's, it's when the change in depth
inside. So when z1 - z2 is small, Relative
to, To z, and that's the setting image we
make Orthographic Projection. So
Orthographic Projection make you just
assume that there's a constant factor of
[inaudible] do to the distance and the
distance is assumed to be approximately
the same for the whole object, Okay, Thank