Okay. Hello? Welcome to the class again.
So this lecture is going to be about the
fundamentals of image formation. So, any
camera creates an image. The image eye of
XY is a measure of how much light is
captured the pixel XY. We are interested
in two questions. First, where is the
point XYZ in the [inaudible] image and
what is the brightness of the resulting
point XY? So, in this lecture, we'll try
to get a handle on the first question
which is where does the point XYZ in the
[inaudible] image? So this is the
so-called pin hold camera model. The
ignore lenses and such for the time being.
Imagine that all the light in the imaging
surface which is at the back here comes
through the pin hole of the camera and
this object therefore we see this point b.
Is imaged to the point [inaudible]. And
let's take note of the coordinate systems
here. The coordinate system here is
located at the pinhole of the camera and
we have the X, Y and Z axis in the vault.
The Z axis is what's called optical axis
of the camera. And then we have the x and
y axis. Notice that in computer version we
very often follow this coordinate system
where y is up and z is away from the
camera. This is a distinct from the
notation usually used in physics where z
is in the direction of the gravity vector.
Okay. Let's stay with this notation. We
also have a quadrant system on the image
plane and that is indicated here by little
x and little y So that little x and little
y notation correspondents to the
coordinates on the image grain of the
camera. So, our goal is going to be to
figure out the relationship between the
coordinates to the point b in the
3-dimensional vault and the, its
coordinates in the projection. And the
basic equation is given by little x - fx
[inaudible] z and little y - fy
[inaudible] z. So. Okay. So, let's derive
this equation. How do we do that? So we're
gonna proof a special case first and this
is about the special case of a point b in
the y z plane. So let's go back to the
events you can remember what's going on
here. We're going to consider the point b
but we consider a special case when it
lies in the y z plane. We're gonna draw
the optical access and we're also going to
show the projection of b in the image
plane. So that's p and this here is the
projection of p, little p. And what are
these distances? This distance, This
distance here is going to be z. This
distance here is going to be F. This
height here is going to be given by upper
case Y. And this Height here is going to
be given by y, little y but actually it's
going to be minus y because the coordinate
system, in the coordinate system the y
axis points upwards. Let's go back so you
can see that I've drawn this correctly. So
if you look at the slide it becomes clear
what I'm trying to do. I'm trying to draw
the coordinates but since the y axis
points up, distance going down should be
marked as -y, okay. So we are back to
this, back to this equation and now we
have a fairly easy job. We use similar
triangles. The two triangles here are
similar to each other so therefore what we
can say is f / -y = z / Y and this implies
that. Y = -f. It's y divided by z. Okay.
Now this was for the special case when the
point P lies in the YZ plane. But really
this is true Even if the point is, Even if
the point P Is not in the y z plane. And
the way you can convince yourself of that
is that all we have to do is to consider
the projection of b on the y z plane and
then the relationship with the two. So we
have derived this, this equation for the
projection of the y coordinate and by
similar reasoning. We can expect that we
will get a relations that is off the type
x = minus F x upon z. So this just states
this and now I've written out this
equation in sort of nice mathematical
notation. So notice a few things here so
there are some conventions here which is
that the lower case quantities are used to
correspond to variables of the image plane
and upper case variables are used for.
Four points which are in the scene, in the
three dimensional scene, So if you notice,
look at this equation. There's one
annoying property of this equation which
is that there are these minus signs The x
- FX upon Z, y - FY upon Z. Now what these
minus signs correspond to is that the
image is inverted. The image is inverted
both upside down as well as left to right.
And this is something you can find
annoying but this is actually true of
projection of images even in the retina
and in fact the diagram that I have is
from the cuts [inaudible]. So, we do this.
The image is in fact actually inverted.
So, this caused many people a lot of
consternation back at once upon a time
even people such as Leonardo Da Vinci and
they proposed various designs of what
could happen in the eye so as to avoid
this emotion not to do the recollection.
But, this is really not so much of a big
deal. The point is that the brain can
interpret the image the right way and for
a camera, it's life is particularly easy
because software can simply flip the image
drop down and right left and after we
apply this trick, what we get is much
nicer looking equations which is x = fX /
ZyF * Y / Z. So we got rid of the issue of
lateral emotion and top down flipping.
Good. So now, we are ready to start to
understand the mathematics of Perspective
projection. And, for this, I have picked
this drawing. It's actually drawing not an
image but since the drawing is trying to
be accurate about perspective, we can
consider this. So, on this, in this image
which let's say corresponds to a camera
taking a picture of some telephone post
and some cat eye and a road and some grass
and so forth, let's try to look for some
phenomena which arise due to perspective
projection. So here's one. Parallel lines
in the image can merge to a vanishing
point so the parallel lines that are
considered here are the feet of the radius
pulls and the tops of the pulls. The tops
of the pulls is constringent at one line.
The free to the pulls corresponds to
another line and the two sides of the
road. And all of these appear to converge
to a vanishing point. So note that this is
a phenomenon of perspective. The Lines
themselves do not meet in 3-dimensional
space they're parallel to each other but
the projection in the image are here to
meet. So can we explain this? Okay. Here's
another observation. So we have that
nearer objects are lowered in the image so
here I denoted y1, y2, y3. The y
coordinates of the feat of these pulls and
you'll notice that the nearer pull has
foot y1 which is closer which is lower in
the image. Nearer objects are bigger. This
again you should not be surprised. So
let's take up some of this properties and
try to prove them mathematically. So first
let's take up this property that parallel
lines can merge to a vanishing point. How
will we go about proving this? So let
there be a point a and a direction vector
d and three dimensional space and what
we'll do now is to write down the equation
of point on this line and what can we say
about that? We can write the equation of a
general point on this line as, here are
the three coordinates x, y and z and these
are equal to A sub x, a sub y, a sub z. +
lambda * D sub x, d sub y, and d sub z. So
x here land so let me draw a picture here
so suppose we have. We have some point a
and the we consider some line going
through it and that direction of this line
is d. And so we'll get a point here which
is a +. D and then there might be a point
here which is a + 2d. And there might be a
point here which is a -d And so on so the
general way to think about it is that we
have this parameter lambda and lambda
ranges between it, it can go to infinity
in one direction or it can go to -infinity
to consider points to the other side.
Okay. So by [inaudible] we get different
points of this line, So let's now if we
get on the projection of this point, how
do we do that? So, what's, let's look at
the x coordinate so we have this equation
x = fx upon z. So if we want to apply
this, we have f * x coordinate. It's going
to be a sub x + lambda d sub x. / what is
the c coordinate. It's going to be a sub
z. + lambda d sub z. Is that clear? Good.
So now what we can do is we want to figure
out what happens to this coordinate of
this projection point as the line goes to
infinity in three dimensional space so how
do we find that? Let's consider Lambda
going to infinity. So then what's gonna
happen? What happens to this expression?
So in this expression, in the expression
for x essentially the dominant dome will
now become lambda dx / lambda dz which
will give you f. D sub x upon d sub z.
Okay? Now, the interesting thing here is
that this expression. This expression Does
not Depend On a So therefore if we have a
family of parallel lines, they all will
have the same direction d but they will go
through different points a but the
projection coordinate x does not depend on
that. So, in general. So what we have
shown is the coordinates of the projection
Rf d sub x upon d sub z For the x
coordinate. And read by analogy we, I
haven't and By doing the same process For
y coordinate We get f d sub y upon d sub z
for the y coordinate, And does F d sub x
upon d sub z, f d sub y upon d sub z The
coordinates Of the vanishing point Of this
family of [inaudible], Okay. Let's take a
break here.