Hello. Welcome back. So, in the last
lecture, we started various properties of
Orthogonal Transformations specifically
rotations and three dimensions. So, by now
you must be wondering Is there more. We
have studied rotations, we have studied
translations. Is there more having the set
of Rigid Body Motions, how should we think
about it in general? And here, there is a
theorem and the theorem is that any Rigid
Body Motion can be expressed as an
Orthogonal Transformation followed by a
translation. So, we don't need to consider
anything other than Orthogonal
Transformations and translations. A manual
Orthogonal Transformations, there are ones
which have determinant plus one and
determinant minus one and we will be
concerned with deter, those
transformations which are determinant plus
one. And something these are called Proper
Rigid Body Motions and deter, special
Orthogonal Group is used. Okay. So, now we
can ask the question, here is a certain
form of this transformation. Can we say
more about the structure of the set of
Rigid Body Transformations, So one
observation here is that the composition
of two isometries is an isometry. So, how
do we go about proving this? So there is
one isometry given by. The formula here
and let's say another isometry given by
this formula. So here, a1 and a2 are the
Orthogonal Matrices. They will correspond
to the rotation part if the determinant is
plus one. And then there's a translation
given by t1 or t2. So, if we combine this
two, do we get another isometry? Well,
that's really straight forward thing. We
just do the algebra so here let's say we
first. We have the point a, we apply psi
two and then we apply psi one so that will
give me this kind of an equation here. And
then if I try to the algebra, I get.
Something else which is a3a + t3 where a3
is a1a2 and the t3 is a1t2 + t1. And this
is again in form of an Orthogonal Matrix
multiplying a vector plus a translation.
So what we see is that composition of two
isometries is therefore an Isometry. Well
generally, Isometry is constit ute a group
in the mathematical sense. And again, if
you don't know the definition if a group,
you can look it up on Wikipedia. So When
you have element of a group and some
operations, we can get new elements of the
group. And, and there has to be an
identity element. So, what will be the
identity isometry. It will correspond to
a. Being i, so the Orthogonal Matrix is i
which does nothing. And the translation
part should then be just zero and that if
I have an Isometry corresponding to an
Orthogonal Matrix which is the identity
and the translation which is zero, I will
have nothing happened as a result of it.
There is an inverse so, if there is a
Isometry specified by the Orthogonal
Matrix a and translation vector t, we can
compute what. Should be the Isometry
applied to the result of the first
transformation so as to bring us back to
the identity and this leave as an exercise
to you. You should be able to work this
out. Isometries are, are the composition
of Isometry is also shared in to that
second, straight forward thing to work
out. Now let's turn to the same form that
transformation is matrix multiplication of
the input vector a and then after that
there's an addition of a translation
vector t. But now what we do is, we
generalize a little bit. What we say is
that a is no longer required to be
Orthogonal, a is any nonsingular Matrix in
this case. Meaning that we require that
it's determinant be, not be zero but
that's it. So you can see clearly that
this is a proper generalization of the set
of isometries or Rigid Body Motions
because Orthogonal Matrices are obviously
nonsingular so everything just works, it's
gonna work out there. But what does this
bias this notion of Affine Transformation?
It's a more general notion, what does it
bias? It buys us more flexibility. So
here, I am going to give you an example
where this is the input, this is the input
and this, for example, you can think of a
four points of the square is input. Now,
there are Orthogonal Transformations we
know about such as rotation, right? That
will do, that will give you something like
this. But Rotations or rotations followed
by translations cannot give you effects
such as an isotropic scaling or share. How
are these can be captured by a fine
transformations? So for example, an
isotropic scaling, Let's just think of
what that matrix a must be. For example,
it could be something like two, zero,
zero, one. If, with a matrix like that,
what will happen is that the x dimension
will get magnified by two, and the y
dimension remains unchanged. So that's an
Isotropic Scaling and this is allowed
under the set of Affine Transforms. And we
can have other kinds of matrices a and
some of these will give rights to shares.
So and obviously Where, rotations are
already included. Okay let's test our
understanding of affine transforms with
isometrics by studying how many parameters
are required to specify an isometry versus
an affine transform. So, let's think about
isometrics. So, isometry in two dimensions
so, in two dimensions, an isometry is a
rotation and how many parameters are
required for that one. Any translation for
that you require two so you need three
parameters to specify an isometry or a
Rigid Body Motion in two dimensions. What
about for Affine transforms? So, they're
gonna have two by two matrix so that has
four parameters. And then the translation
part which will have two parameters, so
therefore, we get a total of six
parameters. Okay now, you may want to
think through what will happen in 3D. If
you want pause over there now and try to
figure it out before I give you the
answer. So, in 3D, either isometry
[inaudible] in orthogonal matrix followed
by translation, So, the orthogonal matrix
are, is gonna have three independent
parameters. And the translation will be
another three parameters For a total of
six. When we consider Affine transforms in
3d, what are we gonna get? We're gonna get
a three by three matrix and so the three y
three matrix will have nine parameters,
and then there will be translation which
is going to be three parameters so for a
total of twelve. So we see clearly that
Affine Transforms are more general, they
require more parameters to specify. So,
the big picture can be understood better
if we try to ask the question, what
remains unchanged under the
transformation. So, mathematically, the
term we use is invariance. What are the
invariance in the transformation. So under
Euclidean Transformations, we design them
to be such that the preserved length. So
if we have two points, the, the, the
distance between them should be unchanged.
That was essentially our definition of
Isometry. So in the Euclidean
Transformations, lengths are preserved,
angles are preserved, as well as area And
volume and so forth. Under Affine
Transforms, we already saw this thing
called an Isotropic Scaling case that
lengths are not preserved, angles are not
preserved, areas are not preserved.
However, some things are preserved.
Remember these Affine Transforms are
Linear Transformations for the better
translation. And, you can see that if two
lines were parallel to begin with. Then,
if we apply a transformation, these two
lines remain lines and they might be moved
about, they might be farther apart, but
they'll remain parallel. Parallel lines
remain parallel. Another nice property is
that the property of being the midpoint
remains. So, supposed I have points A. And
see and then there is a point b which is
the midpoint of a, b, c and now, we
transform by an affine transform. Will,
the line will remain a line. That length
may change. But, let's say the point a
transformed to here and the point c is
transformed to here, the point b will
remain the midpoint. So, that is preserved
and again, you can verify all these from
the properties that you know. Essentially
the fact that there's a Linear Transform
involved makes all these understandable.
Okay, so, so, here are the big picture. We
have the set of affine transforms and
within the set of affine transforms. We
have in there the set of Euclidean
transformed. And specifically there's one
particular point. This is t he, The
identity And this corresponds to a=i and
the translation part being the zero
vector. So, the identity is included in
Euclidean Transforms and of course, the
identity is included in Affine Transforms.
But the next question we can ask is; now
we got a more general set of transforms
and these constitute the group as well.
But all of these as general as we need to
be. Okay? Let's think there is a set of
transformations that are called Projective
Transformations but let me first motivate
why we need that. We studied Prospective
Projection, that's after [inaudible]
version motivation here. Under Prospective
Projection, lines on a ground plane which
will parallel. They projected two lines on
the image plane that intersected. So
parallelism was not a property that was
preserved. And, affine transforms preserve
parallel itself. So, we now know that
Prospective Projection cannot be modeled y
an Affine Transform. And since we want to
play around with Prospective Projection,
we need to consider a more general family
of transformations. The answer is provided
by this family of transformations called
Projective Transformations. These are even
more general that Affine Transforms and
this include Prospective Projection as a
special case. What are Projective
Transformation? These are Linear
Transformations. Okay, so far so easy. In
fact, you don't need to add the
translation parts separately. The
translation can be folded into the Linear
Transformation. But, this used something
called Homogeneous Coordinates. Okay, so
now we have another new piece to explain.
Homogeneous coordinates, I'm really not
going to get into too much detail on this
because this is after of course in
computer vision and not of course on
mathematics. I encourage you to look it up
in Wikipedia. I'll just give you a little
taste of what this whole idea is about.
Supposed we have a point in
three-dimensional r3. So normally, we
might modulate by, by some three vector,
x, y, z, these are the normal Euclidean
coordinates. What we do is we add another
fo urth coordinate. So, we have now
coordinates x1, x2, x3, x4. But the
property is that, any two such vectors are
regarded as the same vector if they are
scaling multiple to each other. So in a
settled sense, the degrees of freedom are
still three. So sometimes you can think of
this as, you can go from x1, x2, x3, x4 by
just dividing by the fourth coordinate.
Now, that's, doesn't do anything very
exciting unless the fourth coordinate is
zero. And that corresponds to the
so-called point of infinity. In fact,
there are many points of infinity, So
homogeneous coordinates enable one to
represent All the things that we have
talked about so far, rotations,
translations, and so forth, all by a
single matrix. So in, when we are
concerned with three dimensional space,
so, in three dimensional space the normal
points would have three coordinate but
Homogeneous coordinates would make us get
to full vectors and so the matrix, that
would be in more for a Linear
Transformation will be a four by four
matrix. Actually, it will have only
fifteen independent parameters because
overall. If, if you might apply all the
entries of this matrix by a non-zero
Scalar, nothing changes because Scalar
multiples correspond to the same point in
projective space. These transformations
are used a lot in computer graphics
because in computer graphics when you want
to render objects, you want to rotate
them, translate them, project them and all
of these can be captured as Linear
Transformations and Homogeneous
Coordination. So the, there is support for
these kinds of computer available in
graphics hardware. I'm going to stop my
coverage of this topic right here because
we'll, we may need to know a little bit
more about Projective Transformations but
we'll develop it as a necessary field that
I don't want the course to become a dry
mathematical review. So I'll just
summarize the final story here. We are
concerned with three main families of
transformations, Projective
Transformations, Affine Transformations,
and Euclidean Transformations. Euclideans
are the most specific. These are Rigid
Body Transformations and they preserve
distances, angles, areas, etc. Affine
Transforms are the more, the next
generalization and Projective is the most
general of all. Thank you.