Okay. Welcome back. So we're going to
study parametrizing rotations in 3D. So
let's take some easy cases. How do we
describe a rotation around the x-axis?
Well, that's pretty easy because the
x-axis, nothing much happens. So that's
where we have this one and then in the yz
we have a 2-by-2 matrix as we would have
encountered before. So this is an easy
thing to do. Let's consider rotation about
the z-axis. And this is also easy. Because
in that... As you'll recall that these are
the X, Y and Z components. So in the X and
Y plane, we have a standard 2D rotation
matrix. In the Z axis nothing much
happens. So that's why we have these
simple rotation matrices. But what do we
do in general? That's the question that
we'll study in this lecture. What about
the general case. So there are many
different ways of specifying rotations and
three dimensions, and let's consider what
they are. First is othogonal
matrices, This is very natural. This
corresponds to the fact that rotation is
linear isometric. But orthogonal matrices
are redundant because you, you have a
three by three matrix, so this corresponds
to nine parameters. But there are really
only three genuine parameters. So these
nine bit entries in the matrix are
redundant. And we've like to get out the
true degrees of freedom of the problem,
which corresponds to axis of rotation and
the amount of rotation. There's some
classic techniques out there. Euler angles
is one of them. Quaternions is another
one. This is generalization of the idea of
complex numbers, which can be used to
represent rotation in two dimensions. To a
technique that once was representing
rotation in three dimensions. This was
quite a big deal when it was when it was
invented in the nineteenth century by
Hamilton who was one of the great
mathematicians and physicists of that
period. [inaudible] the methodI like those things
in a much more direct way. And what it
does is that it tries to give us a way to
go back and forth very simply between
orthogonal matrices and what, what we should think
of as a fundamenta natural
representation which is a specified
rotation by giving the axis of rotation
and the amount of rotation. Once you have
that you should be able to write down the
orthogonal matrix. Conversely given the
orthogonal matrix, we should be able to
write down what facts in a rotation or
amount of rotation. We could do this in
easy case which we saw in the previous
slide. Right? For rotation above the X
axis and rotation above the Z axis, you
could do this. But my question for you is,
suppose I have an arbitrary axis. I just
give you some unit vector in, in three,
and I give you some amount of rotation.
Can you construct the rotation matrix for
me? Conversely I could give you a rotation
matrix and I could tell you okay, tell me
what's the axis of rotation? Tell me
what's the amount of rotation? Before we
proceed with the lecture you may want to
stop it right here and try to think about
how you might do it, and you may real, you
may then realize that's it's, it, it's a
slightly tricky problem. So we'll, in this
lecture we'll figure out an efficient way
to do this. The big idea is that we are
going to represent rotations as
exponentials of Skew Symmetric Matrices.
Okay, so there are some multiples in here,
including the term exponential of a
matrix, skew symmetric matrix. But
hopefully by the end of this lecture, you
will find that all this is very natural.
The skew symetrix matrix is going to turn
out to correspond to the axis of rotation.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to take this axis of rotation. And from
that, we will construct a skew symmetric
matrix. We will then construct the
exponential of a matrix in some way. And
that exponential is going to give me the
orthogonal matrix. That's the basic story.
And then, how do we go back? Essentially,
we, for an exponential, the opposite, the
inverse function is a log. And something
like that will work out here. So let's
start by some review. So you all know the
notion of a vector product or cross product
from physics. So if I'm given two vectors
V1 and V2. I've shown them here as vectors
V1 and V2. We can construct the so called
vector product or cross product, which is
yet another vector W. And, there are
properties of this vector W. It's going to
be in; we construct the plane of V1 and
V2. And then the vector W is going to be
perpendicular to that plane. And its
magnitude is related to the magnitudes of
V1 and V2, and the angle between them. So,
the vector W is perpendicular to the plane
spanned by V1 and V2. So you can review
this if you have forgotten this
definition. I want to just say as well
that I will use an alternative notation,
instead of just using the cross the x I
will use this red wedge symbol. But I use
this for cross product. So, nothing big
deal, just a particular notation that, I
like and is used in more higher
mathematical applications. Okay. The next
thing we need to know about skew-symmetric
matrices. A skew-symmetric matrix is
defined by the property that, a matrix A
is said to be skew-symmetric if A is equal
to minus A transposed. So this is just the
definition. But this definition tells us
something, so you have a three by three
matrix A then it must have zeros in
the diagonal and if it has entries A, B, C
in the off diagonal position here then
entries here minus A, minus B, and
minus C, so it's a three by three matrix but
it has only three parameters. And, what
we're going to do is we're going to take
the axis of rotation. Which is a vector in
three dimensional space. And we are gonna
map it to a skew-symmetric matrix. There
is some black magic involved here, which
will become clear later. Let me just
remind you that in this course and in this
lecture, you may come across concepts that
you are a bit rusty on. You may have
encountered them somewhere in your.
Previous linear algebra or physics class
or also calculus [inaudible] and now you
may have forgotten them. Well, if you need
to revise them just go look them up in
Wikipedia. I find their entries on
mathematical topics to be excellent. Okay.
So now let's build up from this connection
of vector product and skew symmetric
matrices. So, this is just the definition
of vector product, which is the standard
definition of vector product. I'm given a
vector A. And a vector B And then the
vector product is another vector and this
is what the competence will be. So this
you can look up. Here's a new idea. We're
gonna take a vector A. So this is a vector
in three. And we're gonna make a matrix A
HAT Which is a three by three matrix. And
the way we are gonna do this is that we
are gonna take the entries of A and put
them at particular locations in this
matrix. So the vector a has the entries
a1, a2, a3. I take these entries a1, a2,
a3 and I put them in particular locations
of this matrix. And now I've got a new
matrix. So is a three-by-three matrix.
Okay. This is just some little bit of
juggling around. I'm just Nothing big deal
so far. The fun begins here. Given this
matrix, this three by three matrix, an now
I do a vector matrix multiplication. I
multiply a hat and the vector b,
which is given by the three components b1,
b2, b3. And you have to just do this
algebra. Take, take this matrix, and take
this vector, and do the matrix, matrix
vector multiplication. And you will get.
And you'll get this guy which is the same
as this guy So in other words. This matrix
vector product does the same job as
creating the vector product or the, the
cross product that you are familiar with
in physics. So we've established a certain
very natural, simple relationship between
skew symetric matrices and this process of
creating a vector product or cross
product. Okay what's the value of this?
This is just a little mathematical trick.
The value will come soon. For that I have
to build up another notion which is that
of exponentials of matrices. Exponential
of scalars you know, I mean, here's a
classic formula. Each of the x is given by
one + x + x squared upon two victorial +.
so on, that's the Taylor series expansion.
Okay. What is the exponential of a matrix?
So here A is some matrix. What's the exponential of a matrix? It's, it's kind of
a model equivalent of this formula. But
instead of one, what is one in the space
of matrices. Well, multiplying by one
leaves the number unchanged. Multiplying
by what matrix leaves matrix unchanged.
It's the identity matrix. Instead of X,
well, the objects here are matrices, so
this should be A. And this should be A
squared upon two factor. And what do I
mean by A squared? Well, it's matrix
multiplication. Matrix A multiplied by
matrix A, plus the matrix. And so on. So
this is a formal is like a Taylor series,
but we can use this to define the
exponential of a matrix and in certain
programming languages such as in Math Lab.
You, in fact, have a function called EXPM.
So if you do EXPM of A that says matrix
exponential of A. That will, in fact,
compute into the A. So this is really a
perfectly reasonable object just like the
E to the X that you've known and loved
since, the days of high school, really.
Okay. So, why is this idea of matrix
exponential useful? Let's do one more
little trick. Let me remind you that
exponentials are arises solutions of
linear diferential equations. So, suppose we have
the equation. X dot equals AX, where X dot
really stands for DX upon DT is X dot X,
just the standard notation. The solution
to this differential equation is that X as
a function of time is given by X of zero.
This is just the initial condition times
exponential e To the AT. Again, standard
result This idea applies when we have X's
which are vectors. So here, I have this
formula, X dot. But this is now a vector.
And. It's the, the, this is a differential
equation. So what's the solution of this
differential equation? So, that the
solution here is going to be, x of t
equals e to the a t, and then there will
be some initial condition x sub 0. So
this is the initial condition. And this is
of course a vector and A to the t
is of course another vector. But that's my, matrix
exponential. So that's a matrix
exponential. So this is all very nice,
because the notion of, scalar linear
differenti al equations gives rise to an
exponential. Your vector differential
equation, and now you get, matrix
exponential. Okay. So now, proceeding
right along I want to remind you of this
equation which you probably encountered in
freshman physics. So this Omega here is
the angular velocity vector. So, so we
have the position of a point Q and then Q dot
is the time derivative. So Q Is given by
Omega cross product with Q. We can rewrite
this using this new trick that we learned.
Which is that, when we want to con-,
construct a vector product, we, we will,
we will make up a new matrix. Make a hat.
And now we will convert it into a, matrix
factor multiplication And the solution to
this differential equation, so now we got
a linear differential equation. And the
solution to this differential equation is,
as we studied in the last slide, it's
going to be given by the initial condition
Q0 times the matrix exponential e
to the omega hat t. And we can work out
what e to the omega hat t is. It's going
to be given by this Taylor series. Now we
actually don't have to Computed in this,
way Which is, to really compute each of
these terms and then add them up. There's
much more efficient ways of doing this.
And the reason why there much more
efficient ways of doing this is because
these terms omega hat t omega hat t
square omega hat t cubed omega hat t
to the fourth power and so on. These are
not all independent After a while. What
you, if you work these out, by brute force
calculation, you'll find that they start
to repeat. So you can group these terms
together, and so on, and so forth. And,
I'll give you a little flavor of that by
showing how we can calculate the second
term in the series, the square term. So
the square term will correspond to
the product of, two skew symmetric
matrices, and I've shown those here. If
you work this out, so suppose we have the
matrix S hat, and then we have S hat
squared, which is the product of these two
matrices. Well, that will turn out to
SS transposed minus I. And this is a
straight algebra thing to do. But let's go
back to the formula. It turns out that if
we collect these even, odd and even terms,
can do a little bit of work along the
lines that I had just illustrated. You can
derive a very beautiful formula, and that
beautiful formula is called Rodriguez
formula, and it is given by this
expression. This is really a beautiful
formula. Why? Because given an axis of
rotation. And what's the axes of rotation?
The axes of rotation here is given by S.
And the axes of rotation here corresponds
to this omega vector, normalized. So I
have taken the omega vector and divided by
its, its magnitude. So I have a unit
length vector S. Given this unit vector S
I can make up a matrix, three-by-three,
skew symmetric matrix and put that here.
Okay. What is phi? Phi is the total amount
of rotation and that is given by the
angular velocity, omega multiplied by
time. So the angular velocity might
be radiance per second, time as in
seconds, so five would be measure in
radiance. So if you look at Rodriguez's
formula here, we have S had and S had
squared which are these skew symmetric
matrices that you can construct if you
know the axis of rotation, S. And then we
have five, which is the amount of
rotation, which you know. So given these V
have the ability to construct R, which is
the total rotation matrix. So if you want
to think about this conceptually, the S
hat, the axis of rotation, in a way, it
specifies. Infinite similar rotation,
what happens in a very, very small amount
of time. Now this process, when you carry
it for a finite amount of time, that's
what gives rise to the finite rotation,
which is R. So it's really a
relationship between a rotation when a
finite amount of time has elapsed to the
amount of change when a very, very small
amount of time has elapsed. It's some
intuitive sense. But this relationship
here is a mathematically rigorous
relationship. I'm trying to just hand wave
my way to give you an intuition about
this. Okay, now we have achieved our grand
goal, which is, how do we go from notation
matrices to an axis angle representation
of [inaudible]. So how do I go from, given
an axis of rotation S, and an amount of
rotation theta to R? Well, from S, we can
construct this S hat. So S is a vector,
and this is the skew symmetric matrix. And
then we can do, just this exponential and
that gives me R. Now, this can be
simplified further and that is Rodriquez
formula. Okay. So that's how we can go
from an access and a mount [inaudible]
rotation to the matrix R. How do we do the
converse problem? I give you a three by
three rotation matrix and I want you to
tell me what's the axis of rotation and
what's the amount of rotation. Well, you
actually can do the equivalent, the
inverse of exponential, which is, log. And
it turns out that in math lab, there is,
in fact, a command by which you can take
the log of the R matrix, and that will
give you theta S hat. But there are other
ways. Let me show you how we can get the
angle theta, the total amount of rotation.
Well, it turns out that the trace of
R. And what's the trace of R? It's
the sum of the diagonal entries. This is
equal to one plus two cosign theta and you
can verify this from Rodriguez formula. So
since we know what the rotational matrix
are we can compute theta so we know
the amount of rotation. What about the
axis of rotation? What can we do? Well,
here is one observation, compute the
eigen vector of R corresponding to
eigen value One Because what, what,
what's the property of the access of
rotation? When you apply the rotation, the
points which lie on the access do not
change. So that's why they must correspond
to an eigen vector of eigen value 1. So
that's why we're doing it. But there are a
zillion other ways. You can take Rodriguez
formula and manipulate it around. So, use,
You can use Rodriguez. And you can have R
and the matrix R transposed. And then from
these, you can kind of pull out S hat. And
once we have the S hat matrix, you can
easily read out the, the axis of rot
ation. So we have, thus, achieved our
grand goal which is to be able to go back
and forth between rotation matrices, which
are orthogonal matrices, three-by-three
matrices, to an axis of rotation
representation. Now we can choose
whichever one makes more sense for our
purposes.