Hello again, So in the last lecture we
studied the definition of an Orthogonal
Matrix. And an Orthogonal Matrix is
defined by this condition, a transposed a
= i and a is an Orthogonal Matrix. Or we
can say a is the matrix associated with an
Orthogonal Transformation. Right, Why do
we care about this matrices? Let's let the
cat out to the bag, Because Rotations And
reflections Are Orthogonal
Transformations. So, we're gonna set this
up in the second. Let's first consider
the, these Orthogonal Matrices in general
and derive a few of their properties. And
from those properties we will see in fact
that Orthogonal Matrices are exactly two
kinds. Either they are rotation or they
are reflections. So, let's figure this
out. So, let's, let's take this
relationship a transpose to a = i and
derive some consequences. So, one
consequences, some properties. One is that
a transpose just a inverse, I showed that
last time. The second property is based on
the fact. That it, we will show that the
determinant of a is =,,,, + or - one. How
do we show this proof? Whenever we have
matrices if. C is = ab if a matrix c is
the product of matrices a and b, then
Determinant of c is the product of
determinant of a * the determinant of b,
okay? So, let's apply that relationship
here. So therefore Determinant of a
transposed * the determinant of a is going
to be = one. So, we showed that the
determinant of a transposed * the
determinant of a = one. Now, we know That
the determinant of the transpose of a
matrix is the same as the determinant of
the matrix. So therefore, determinant of a
squared is = one. This implies that the
determinant of a is. Equal to plus one or.
To determinant of a is equal to -one. So,
this is a very important property because
we have a name for these two kinds of
matrices. And the determinant of a+1 is
equal to the rotation. And when the
determinant of a is -one, we call that a
reflection. And you know? Little while
you'll see why we choose these terms. But
for now, just, you just can see that for
any Orthogonal Matrix, it must be the case
that the determinant is +one or -one, we
just give names to these two categories.
We call one of them rotations and the
other one reflections. Okay. Okay, let's
study another property and this is going
to be that the columns of, The columns of
a are orthonormal. Okay, what do I mean by
that? Let's first write out a. So, a is
some matrix and let's say that, let's do
it in two dimensions. So, let's say that
this is sum vector a1 and sum vector two,
So, for Two by two, Okay? So far so good.
Now, what do we know about such a matrix?
What is a transpose is going to be. A
transposed is going to be Row vector
corresponding to a1 and row vector
corresponding to a2. And we know. That a
transpose to a = i. But let's calculate
what a transpose a is. And let me switch
to a different color. What is a transposed
a? A transposed a is going to be this,
let's figure out what those entries are
gonna be. This entry is going to be a1
transposed a1. This entry is going to be
a2 transposed a2. And this entry is going
to be a1 transposed. A2 and this will be
a2 transposed a1. Okay? But, the key point
is that this product of a transposed a is
equal to the identity. And this tells me
that therefore A1 transposed to a1 must be
equal to one, A1 transposed a2 must be
equal to zero and the same is true for a2
transposed a1 and a2 transposed A2 = one.
So, let's repeat what we said, a is equal
to. So, a is a1 and a2, these are column
vectors. And the short That. Okay, but
what does that mean? That means that the
columns are orthonormal. By that, I mean
what's the length of a1. What's the length
of a1? It's the same as the length of a2
and the, this length is one and that
follows from. That follows from this
property and, And from this observation
that we had. What else do we know? We
know, so therefore, each column is of
length one and. We also know that a1
transpose to a2 is zero. And where did we
see that? We saw that here. So that says
that each column is of length one and if I
take the dot product of two of these colu
mns, that gives you zero. So it's a very
pretty situation. This means that,
essentially. A1 and a2 are Vectors of
length one. Which are mutually
perpendicular? So in other words, you can
use a1 and a2 to make an orthogonal basis.
And this is gonna be true in any
dimension. In dimension two, dimension
three and so forth. So, in dimension two,
so let's take up the case of dimension
two, In r2. If we have that a1 is a column
vector which is of length one, a1 is
Cosine theta, sine theta. We can pick such
vector without laws [inaudible] of because
we know that a1 has to be of length one.
So, we can just call this cosine theta
sine theta, okay? So, what must a2b? Well,
we know that a2 should also be of length
one and a2 has to be. The length of a2
should be one and it should be the case
that a1 transposed a2 is = zero. So I,
what choice do I have? I essentially have
two choices now. I can make a2. So, that
gives me two choices for a2. Either I
could pick minus sign theta cosine theta.
Or. I could pick Sine theta - cosine
theta. So, I really have only these two
choices. Because the property of these two
choices is that they both have length,
they are of length one that's easy to
identify. But in addition, they are
perpendicular. Okay, but what does this
mean? This essentially tells me that the
matrix a, I have only two choices of this
matrix a. This is one choice, cosine theta
sine theta - sine theta cosine theta. This
is one choice Or a is Cosine theta sine
theta, Sine theta Minus cosine theta, This
is the other choice. And that is it. The
matrix a has an orthogonal matrix and two
dimensions can be on only these two
points. Okay, let's calculate what the
determinant of this matrix is and what's
the determinant here. If you work it out,
cosine theta * sine theta is cosine
squared theta + sine squared theta, the
determinant here is +one. In this case,
what is the determinant? It's minus cosine
squared theta - sine squared theta. So,
the determinant here is -one. And recall
that I said that for any Orthogonal Matrix
the determinant is either + one or - one.
And let's now try to get a physical
picture of this. So, so suppose we have A
vector Xy And then consider A * xy, and i
Cosine theta - sine theta sine theta
cosine theta * xy. And this is really
counter clockwise Rotation by theta Which
is very nice. And so we have a, a, you can
convince yourself that this is true by
starting off with what happens with the
vector one, zero. So, One, zero gets
transformed. And the answer is it gets
transformed to cosine theta, sine theta.
So, if we want to set up a little diagram.
So if we had this initial vector, then
after this rotation, it's going to go to.
This angle is theta. And, If we had a
vector here, that vector is going to go
to. So, this is counterclockwise Rotation
[inaudible] theta. So, in two dimensions,
the story therefore is very simple.
There's two kinds of Two kinds of
Orthogonal Matrices And these are of the
type cosine theta - sine theta. Sine
theta, Cosine theta, Or Cosine theta sine
theta, Sine theta - cosine theta. These
have Determinant + one determinant - one,
these are rotations, And these are
reflections. Okay, I'm not going to derive
this here but you can verify That the
reflection matrix here Corresponds to
Reflection Around The line With angle
Theta equals That angle theta divided by
two. Okay, so now let's go to three
dimensions. In 3D, we'll, Consider the
basic properties of rotations. So, we are
going to have again a matrix with three
column vectors, a1, a2, a3. And, similar
reasoning as in the one [inaudible] Has in
the [inaudible]. The length of each of
these column vectors is going to be. One
and The dot product of any two of them is
zero. So, in other words, a1, a2, a3, they
caused upon to a nice orthogonal basis
rather an orthonormal basis because each
of these of unit length. Now in the case
of two dimensions, we could characterize
the rotation by just one angle theta. In
three dimensions, it's a bit more
complicated. We need to specify a rotation
in a more complex way and it turns out
that. We need thr ee parameters To specify
a rotation and. Phi a rotation in 3D. So
let's see if we can convince ourselves of
that. But, how do we think about this
intuitively and we'll think about it as
algebraic as well. So, intuitively How
will you specify a rotation in 3D. We need
to specify an axis about which the
rotation takes place and then we need to
specify an amount of rotation. So, how
many degrees of freedom does the axis
have? Since the axis is a unit length
vector, this means that we need two
parameters to specify the axis. The
rotation is some angles, so that's one. So
therefore we need two + one Equals three
parameters. So that's one way to think
about it. Let's think about it another way
looking at the matrix From the matrix. How
can I choose a1? How many degrees of
freedom do we have for choosing a1? We can
choose a1 by specifying two parameters.
The reason is that the length of a1 is
constrained; it must be of unit length. So
therefore, I can pick a1 with two
parameters. Then, how many parameters do I
have for a2? A2 has to be perpendicular to
a1, okay? So that in fact specifies a
plane in which a2 must lie. It has to be
of unit length so I just can choose very
not plane to pick this unit vector so I
will get one parameter. And once I pick a1
and a2, the third, the third vector is
constrained. It has to be perpendicular to
both them so in fact, it's going to lie
along the vector product of this. So, a3,
it adds no new parameters. So if you add
it up, we get three parameters. So this
algebraic way of looking at the columns of
the Orthogonal Matrix and using the fact
that the columns must be orthonormal gives
us the same count that there are three
parameters which are needed for specifying
rotation matrix. And I got exactly the
same count three when I considered the
fact that any rotation has to be specified
by an axis and an amount of rotation. And
the next lecture will continue with how we
can specify rotations in a convenient way
and three dimensions.