Hello, So, let's continue with our lecture
on Rigid Body Motions. So, in the last
lecture we studied the definition of Rigid
Body Motions which is that if I have
points a and b then, the length before the
transformation is the same as the length
after the transformation, That's the
definition. And then we did an example,
And the example was translation. And
translation is defined as point a gets
mapped to the point a + t and you can
think of t as the shift. Okay, in today's
lecture we'll focus on rotations. And what
I'm gonna do is to try to formally define
rotations and just give you the
mathematical and openings of working
comfortably with rotations. So rotations
of two main properties, they are, first
they are Linear Transformations. What do I
mean by Linear Transformations? So Linear
Transformation, if we have points supposed
a gets mapped to psi of a And b gets
mapped to psi of b. Then if I have the
point alpha a + beta b that should be
mapped to alpha psi of a + beta * psi of
b, This is the definition Of a Linear
Transformation. Okay, that's one way to
think about it abstractly in a
mathematical sense. But there is a more
practical way to think about it which is
that, suppose a is a vector. Another way
Is that psi of a is given by a matrix
times a vector a. So here, let's get our
notation right. This is a matrix. And this
is a vector. Okay, let's take up another,
let's state this more clearly. So, so
suppose we have a We have points in r2,
Then a is A vector Eg, A1, a2, And any
Linear Transformation Corresponds to a
matrix multiplication. So let me indicate
this by psi of a is going to be some
matrix. Let's use b11, b12, b21, b22.
Multiplying this vector a. So in other
words, the vector a by, if we will
multiply by some matrix b * this vector a,
we get the result of this Linear
Transformation. And what we can show is
any Linear Transformation can be expressed
by such a matrix multiplication. So, we
can think equivalently in, in this matrix
notation. So I, I'd like to have my points
Are going to be column v ectors. And so if
we have transformations, Linear
Transformations From two dimensional space
to two dimensional space are represented
by Two by two matrices Has Here And if we
are in three-dimensional-space. Then A
point is Of type B1, b2, b3. So, it's a
column vector And any Linear
Transformation From R3 to r3 Corresponds
to Multiplication by Three by three
matrixes. So we might have a matrix A11,
a12, a21, a21, a22, a23, a31, a32, a33 and
then. We have b1, b2, b3. And this gives
me some new column vector. Let's use the
notation c for this, c1, c2, c3. So, this
corresponds to c is the product of Matrix
Multiplication. In this way and. Is the
matrix, a here is the matrix corresponding
to the Linear Transformation. Okay. So,
this is just standard a Linear Algebra.
Any Linear Transformation can be expressed
by a matrix and matrix is obviously a
Linear Transformation. So, let's go back
to Rigid Body Motions. So, we want to
understand Rigid Body Motions That are
also Linear Transformations. Okay, how do
we do that? So I mean I so we, we, we need
to somehow study the condition of Rigid
Body Motion and add that condition to that
of being a Linear Transformation. So,
we're gonna add a little definition here
And Orthogonal Transformation Is a Linear
Transformation That preserves In a
product. So, that's the definition of
Orthogonal Transformation. So suppose that
we have, we have a and we have b. And a
gets mapped to psi a and b gets mapped to
psi b. What do I mean by inner product?
So, the inner product before the
transformation is given by a dot product
with b, and the inner product after the
transformation is given by psi of a dot
product with psi of b. And these two are
equal. And for those of you who have
forgotten what I mean by inner product A
dot b Is also called Scalar Product. So,
if a is a1a2 and b is b1b2 and I express
them as column vectors that ab = a1b1 +
a2b2. Okay. So, this is the definition.
So, essentially what I'm saying is in a
product preserved, any transformations
which have this property, any Lin ear
Transformation which have this property is
called an Orthogonal Transformation. So
let's try to understand this some
properties of Orthogonal Transformations.
So, one property is that Orthogonal
Transformations preserve norms. So if I
had point a. Okay. So, what do I know? If
I have a, that gets transformed to psi of
a. And let's consider now again the point
a, and that gets transformed to psi of a.
Now consider the dot product before the
transformation, that is going to be a dot
a. So this is before. And now let's
consider the dot product after the
transformation, psi of a dot psi of a. And
this is the dot product after the
transformation. Okay. And by the property
that this Orthogonal Transformation
preserves norms, what do we know? These
two must be equal. Okay, Then, let's write
the south. This means that norm of a
squared = the norm of psi of a. Squared.
So clearly, the norm has been preserved.
In other words, length is being preserved.
So, this might lead you to think that
Orthogonal Transformations are consistent
with the concept of Rigid Body
Transformations. But let's prove this more
generally. So, what we have to do now is
to show this. So, more generally We're
gonna have some point a and this point is
gonna get transformed to psi of a. We're
gonna have a point b, and that's gonna be
transformed to psi of b. And what do we
need to show? We need to show That is
equal to If Psi is a, Is an Orthogonal
Transformation. So that's something to be
proved. So how do we prove this? So, let's
do the following. Let's consider. The
length of psi a - psi b, and what is that
going to be? So this is going to be. So,
that's the length of psi a and psi b. And
the question is, is this equal to the
length of. So we don't know whether this
is true but that's what we'll try to
prove. If we can manage to show that the
two of these are equal, we are in
business. So we can expand this out so I'm
putting a question mark here to imply that
we don't know whether this is true or not.
So what do we get? If we. Expand this out,
we are going to get. So, that's what we
get in the left-hand side and the question
is, is this equal to. What we get on the
right-hand side. Okay. Now, let's make
some observations which we'll do on the
side. So, we have earlier showed that. And
we are sure that. Okay, we showed this in
the previous page. So, that's good. So,
and what else do we know? We know that.
Psi of a dot psi of b is = a dot b. So,
these are all true. And one of this is
true by definition and these were proved
and these do approved Previously. Okay,
So, now we are in business. We are trying
to ask the question Is this expression
equal to this expression? Okay, but we
have and we can use some properties here.
So we just showed that psi of a squared is
= a squared. So the length of psi of a is
the same as the length of a. So this
enables us to cancel this guy, these two
guys are the same. The length of b after
the transformation is the same as the
length of b before the transformation. So,
therefore this and this are the same. And
we also showed that psi a dot product with
psi b is the same as a dot product with b.
And therefore, this term and this term are
the same And this is great. Excellent, So,
we are very happy because we have shown
that these are, these two are. Equal. So,
in other words we have proven This result.
Okay, but what does this mean? What this
means is that. Therefore, psi is a Rigid
Body Motion. So, let me summarize the
result. So, the result is that An
Orthogonal Transformation Is A Rigid Body
Transformation. So just to remind you, we
started with the definition of Orthogonal.
Was that it is linear And it preserves
inner products. Okay, So, in other words A
dot b = psi of a dot psi of b. And the
definition of Rigid Body Transformation
Was that The length of a - b is the same
as the length of psi a - psi of b. And,
what did we proved? We proved That
Orthogonal Transformations are rigid, Have
Rigid Body Transformations. Okay, And, and
recall that earlier we proved That
translations Are Rigid Body
Transformations. So there' s, we have two
examples of this.