Hello, So, let's continue with the
properties of Orthogonal Transformations
and now what we're gonna do is to study
them by the matrices corresponding to this
transformations. And why do we care? The
reason why we care is that rotation is an
Orthogonal Transformation and we need to
have a really good expertise with, to
dealing with rotations and [inaudible]
revision. So, I'm gonna take you through a
mat like chair which is on properties of
rotations. But we're gonna, rotations are
special classes of Orthogonal
Transformations. It turns out the two
kinds of Orthogonal Transformations.
[inaudible] rotations And the other
reflections. But, let's get to this in a
second. What I'm gonna do is, we are gonna
study Orthogonal Transformations Through
the matrices. So, Orthogonal
Transformation are Linear Transformations
and therefore they correspond to, matrix
multiplication. What we're gonna do is to
study properties of those matrices. So,
supposed we have a point B represented by
a column vector. We have an Orthogonal
Transformation psi which corresponds to A
matrix A. So therefore, psi of the point,
applied to the point b is really the
matrix a Multiplied with the column at the
b. So, we know that this is a Orthogonal
Transformation. And What can we say about
its matrix? As an Orthogonal
Transformation, it has some special
properties. What does that imply about the
matrix a? We call The matrix Associated
With an Orthogonal Transformation An
Orthogonal matrix. So, in other words, we
are gonna start to study properties of
Orthogonal Matrices. Okay, let's do that.
So let's start to use the definition Of an
Orthogonal Transformation. So let's say we
have two vectors, a and b. So, a dot
product with b is the same as psi of a dot
product with psi of b, okay? But now, what
is psi of a? This is a * a where a is the,
big A is the matrix, Corresponding to the
transformation To psi And, psi of b Is A *
b, okay? So let's capture this. So we want
to show that a dot b is the same as psi of
a * dot product with psi of b. So, how's t
hat gonna work out? How do I compute? So
what's the dot product in, in matrix with,
with the notation, With matrix notation?
So, let's take an example. We want to
compute the dot product of two vectors, a
and b. And this is really the same as you
take the transpose of the vector a and
then you do a matrix vector multiplication
with b. So, suppose a was a three by one
vector and b was a three by one vector,
what is a transpose is going to be? It's
the one by three vector and b is going to
be a three by one vector. And when we do
the multiplication and this way we get a
one by one vector which the [inaudible]
number. So, this is a standard way To Get
scalar product. Okay. So let's go back to
our condition. The dot product of a and b
must be the same as the dot product of psi
a and psi b. This is by definition. Okay?
So, let's rewrite this. This is gonna be a
transpose b. Now we are thinking in terms
of vector notation. Vectors and what is
psi of a going to be? This is going to be
a, A dot product with ab. Okay, How do I
capture this dot product? What I have to
do is to take the transpose draft on this
case. So, aa transpose ab. And let's
simplify that out, that gives me a
transposed a transposed ab. Okay, let's
rewrite this. Therefore, a transpose b = a
transposed. So, this is a relationship
which is true For all choices Of a and b.
So, just for simplicity Consider a and b
in r2. So therefore, there are Two by one
column vectors. So we can now consider A
and b to be [inaudible] Unit vectors,
various choices of basis vectors, 01 or
Ten. So, for example We could have Ab 1,0
and 1,0. So, like a unit vector along the
x-axis. And what we know is that a
transpose b is = a transposed, a transpose
ab. Definition of Orthogonal
Transformation. Okay. So, but, now we can
take these particular specific examples.
So, if Br, Then what do we get? So a
transpose b will give me one. Okay, That's
what we get on the left hand side. What
happens on the right hand side? On the
right hand side, I have. One, zero
transposed. Then I have this matrix a
transposed a. And let's just call this
matrix c11, c12, c21, c22. And what I have
done is, I defined c to be the matrix a
transposed a. And, here I have 1,0. Okay.
So let's simplify this further. This gives
me zero. So, it gives me one Zero, C11,
c12, c21, c22, One, zero. And what is this
going to give me? This essentially selects
out c11. And now, we know that these two
relationships together tell us that c one,
one must be equal to one. So, let, let's
just pause a little bit so that we are not
totally lost. What I did was, I had a
relationship which I wanted to, I wanted
to study the properties of a transposed a.
And what I did was I picked up particular
choice of the vector a and a particular
choice of the vector b. And, from that I
showed that this matrix a transposed a,
which I'm calling c, has the property that
c11 is = one. And I can now try out
different choices of a and b which will
effectively select different entries in c
And By, By this kind of process We can
show That c is the identity matrix one,
one, zero, zero. And this is, of course,
the matrix a transposed a. Now this is
really not that surprising because if you
recall my basic set up a transposed b was
a transposed * this matrix a transposed
ab. And if that kind of leads one to
expect that this matrix must be the
identity matrix I, where i Is the identity
matrix one, zero, zero, one. So that's
what we have shown. So, So, what we have
shown is that And sometimes, this is used
as a definition. This is used as
definition, As the definition of an
Orthogonal Matrix. In other words, a
matrix a is said to be Orthogonal if it
has the property that a transposed a = i.
Okay, So, let's plug ahead, a transposed a
= i. Actually, you can see a lot from
this. So, I'm gonna just try to derive
some conclusions [inaudible]. This just
says that a transpose is equal to the
inverse of the matrix a because the
property of an inverse obviously is that a
* a inverse should be equal to the
identity and here a transpose will serve
as the rule. So, this is very nice. This
means that when we want to find the
inverse of an Orthogonal Matrix, all you
do is you just transpose it. The rules
become columns and vice versa and now
you've got the inverse, so this is very