Hi, welcome to the class again. And in
this lecture, we are gonna study Geometric
Transformations, the rations and
translations. So, you might be wondering
why we need to have this lesson on Linear
Algebra. The reason we need to have this
lesson in Linear Algebra is because we
want to understand how a camera captures
an image of an object in the world and
what happens if the camera moves. So,
that's what we wanna understand. So, there
are two things involved here. So, imagine
that we have a camera. And in that camera,
we have a coordinate system. So, in the
coordinate system with the camera, we are
going to have x, y, and z. Coordinates
associated with various points in the
object. Right, Now, what happens if this
object moves? So, all these coordinates
will change. Coordinates change. Now, is
this, is this really fundamental? Suppose
I have a chair and I moved the chair, is
the chair now a different object? In a
setting sense, no, it's the same object
but if I measure the coordinates with
respect to the camera, those have changed.
So we want to distinguish between these,
these two effects and we use these two
terms in computer version. One is pause
and the other is shape. So, pose refers to
the relationship of the object to the
camera. And it's gonna be characterized by
how it is situated with the respect to the
camera. So if I am looking at an object
and then I moved that object, then the
pause changes, But the shape doesn't
change. The shape is, changes only if I
break that object or tear it apart or some
such thing, is independent Of the
relationship of the object to the camera.
So, let me illustrate this with an example
from high school Geometry. So, suppose I
have a triangle. And then I, I can move
it. So, I can move it to some new place
and I can rotate it at the same time. So,
what happened is that I have translated
each. And I have rotated it. But it's the
same triangle. So, in high school
Geometry, we call this the Notion of
Congruence. So, we'll say that these two
triangles Are congruent. And there ar e a
number of conditions under which, by which
we can figure out whether the two
triangles are congruent. So, we want to
develop this idea more generally. And
basically, what we are gonna come to is
some notion that there's certain
transformations you can do and that does
not change the shape. So, shape Of the
triangle Remains unchanged Under The
transformation Of rotation and
translation. Note, The coordinate's Xy Of
radius points on the triangle have
changed. So, that's the fundamental
distinction Pose Changes When we rotate
and translate the object, Shape Does not.
Okay, So, that motivates the study of
rotations and translations. So, let's
think about this more generally. So, we
have rotations. And I'm just trying to
rely on your intuition of what rotations
are and translations. And now we will
operate like mathematicians. Are these
Special cases Of more general
transformations? That's the question. And
the answer is yes, And these special class
of transformations I call Rigid Body
Transformations. And Rigid Body
Transformation include rotations and
translations as special cases. Sometimes
we will use the term Isometry as well.
Okay, what do I mean by Rigid Body
Transformation? So let's think of what we
mean by the word rigid body. A rigid body
is characterized by the fact that if there
are any points on that rigid body, they
have the same relationship with respect to
each other as the object moves. So, If I
have let's say a q. So, I consider this
cube And then I can take some points on
this cube. And if I move this by some
rotation and translation. What will
happen? What will happen is that, the
distance is Between any pair of points
Will remain unchanged, Right. If you move
the object, the distance between these,
The distance between these two points will
remain the same. So this distance Stays
Constant. So, we know that this happens
for the rotation and translation. Now,
let's think of some objects when this
won't be the case. So, now I will try to
draw a balloon. Okay? And now what happens
to this balloon is that we blow up this
balloon, it becomes much bigger. So if I
have points a and b, Now, these points are
much farther apart, a prime and b prime.
So, the distance Between A prime and b
prime is unequal to the distance Between A
and b. And in this example of the balloon,
This is Not A Rigid Body Motion. Okay. So,
we have seen some examples, an example of
a Rigid Body Motion and an example which
is not a Rigid Body Motion. So, now let's
get into the math of this and we have
define this formally so now we have the
formal definition. Rigid Body Motion Is a
transformation That preserves Distances.
Okay, so let's state this more precisely.
Suppose I have point a, this is in three
dimensional space and I have some point b
and this is also in three dimensional
space. Now, I apply some transformation
and let's see what is the notation psi for
this transformation. And, this gives me
the new location of the point psi a and
the new location of the point b which is
psi b. So, how do I measure the distance
between a and b? So, what is the distance
between a and b. Well, this is given by
the length of the vector corresponding to
the difference between the vectors a and
b. So this is just a notation for length.
So, just to remind you, suppose we have a
vector. Vector v which is has three
components, v1, v2, v3 then the norm of v.
None of v is given by B1 squared + b2
squared + b3 squared and then you take a
square root of this whole thing. So, this
is the notion of length which you studied
in high school and in Linear Algebra
classes. So, what we do here is we, we
take the difference between the vectors a
and b and the we compute the length of the
difference and that's the distance between
a and b. Okay. So the, so now let's use
this notation here. So, what's the
distance here. So the distance is going to
be the norm of the difference between a
and b and what's the difference here? It's
psi of a is the point after, is the point
a after the transformation and psi of b is
the point b after the transformation and
we take the l ength of this difference.
So, 8f psi is a, So, we can now define
this. If Psi is a Rigid Body
Transformation Then the length of a - b is
equal to the length of psi of a - psi of
b. Okay, so that's my definition. So, you
can't really argue with this because this
is the definition. Okay, so mathematicians
always start with some definition inspired
by, by physical considerations and that's
what we have done here. We want to allow
for the case when an object moves without
breaking apart or stretching or some such.
We have been inspired by physical
considerations to define the notion of
rigid body transformation but now we are
going to mathematically precise
definition. And what we will do now is to
just. Try to follow through on this
definition. So, now we'll kind of operate
like mathematicians who use the physical
world as inspiration for some definitions
but then they tried to find examples,
proof theorems and so on and so forth. In
our case, these are going to be about
rotations and translations. But first I
have to prove that rotations and
translations are Rigid Body
Transformations and this is what I will
try to do next. So, let's consider
examples, First is translation, A Rigid
Body Motion. That's my question, is it?
Well, let's define what is translation.
So, translation is that you just shift an
object by some amount. So the if I have a
Point a, after the transformation it's
going to be a + some shift which I'm
indicating by t. Right? So, that's the
definition of translation. So, this is the
definition of translation, Okay. Can we
check That this Is a Rigid Body Motion.
How do we do this? Okay, so if we have the
point a that's gonna get transformed to a
+ t. If we have the point b, that's going
to get us from 2b + d. Okay. We have some
difference here between the point a and b,
so this is the distance, this is the
original distance. And now, let's figure
out the distance between these guys. So,
the distance between this guy is going to
be given by A Plus t minus B + t, Correct?
And what is this going to be e qual to?
This is going to be equal to the distance
Because the t is canceled out. So this was
the, the old distance was given. So, this
is the new distance. Let me indicate here.
And the important point is that. These two
distances are the same. Few, that's very
comforting and we have convinced ourselves
that translation is a Rigid Body Motion.
Okay let's take a brake here.