Hello, welcome to the class again. And,
finally we start to see some vision
applications of all the math that we
studied on rotations and translations. So
in this lecture we're gonna study dynamic
perspective. The question is what happens
when a camera moves? A moving camera gives
us a lot more information than a static
camera. It gives us information about
depth in the scene. And it reveals what
the so called ego motion is. Ego means I,
so therefore, ego motion means the
movement of the camera. So, let's proceed.
So let me remind you of the pinhole
camera. We studied this in earlier
lectures. So, there, there is some object
out in the world, and that projects to an
image, and we have the standard equations
of perspective projection. We derived them
earlier, but I will in fact consider
simpler versions of those, where first of
all we get rid of the negative sign, and
then secondly we can as well assume that F
is equal to one. Assume f is equal one,
and why is that allowed? We can just
measure everything in units of focal
length. So then the equations will become
x equals. Upper case XO, divided by Z. And
little y is upper case Y divided by Z. So
those are, those are straightforward
simple, simplified versions of the
equations for pinhole camera, the pinhole
camera model of prospective prediction.
Okay. So what happens when the camera
moves with respect to the world? So when a
point XYZ in the world moves relative to
the camera, its projection in the image,
which we use lowercase letters for xy,
moves as well. This movement in the image
plane is called optimal flow. So suppose
that the point XY moves to the point X
plus delta XY plus delta Y in time delta
T. Then we, we can divide delta XY delta
T. And that's considered the X component
of the optical flow. And we can divide
delta Y by delta T, and that's considered
the Y component of the optical flow. So
the optical flow is a vector. It's a two
dimensional vector, and at every point. Xy
in the image. So let's take an example. So
the example that I'm showing here is that
you do a J.J. Gibson. Gibson was a
psychologist who emphasized the importance
of optical flow, for vision perception. So
in this diagram what you see is the
optical flow, for a pilot landing a plane.
So when a pilot is trying to land the
plane, let's say this is where he is going
to land. And what you see here is the
runway. What the pilot will see, as he or
she approaches the runway, is that, the
various points on the ground will appear
as if they are streaming out. It's the
same sensation that you get when you are
driving, when you're driving through a
tunnel. And this, these vectors, these are
these two dimensional vectors. Each of
these vectors is the u, v. The x component
is u, and the y component is v. And these
obviously are functions of x, y because at
a location here, they point outwards and
to the right. At a location here they
point outwards and to the left, and so
forth. So that's why we use the term
vector field Because we have a vector at
every point And as a function of X and Y,
the vector can vary from point to point.
Let's take up another example, also due to
Gibson. This is what the optical flow
field looks like from the side window of a
car. So imagine that you're driving on a
f-, on a highway and you're looking out
from the side, So all these vectors here
correspond to the optical flow And that's
pretty straight forward. Notice that the
vectors are of different lengths. So these
vectors are big, and the vectors here are
small. Well why is that? Well they. That
corresponds to the fact that those points
are far away. The alignment is not moving.
The ground is not moving. What's moving is
the car. So the relative velocity is, is
given by the fact that if the car is
moving at. Some translational velocity T,
the ground is moving relative to it at
minus T. So all the points in the ground
undergo the same movement, but there are
some points which are nearer to you, those
will give rise to bigger optical flow
vectors and there are points which are far
away and those will cause small optical f
low vectors. But this example directly
tells you that we have some information
here to tell us about the depth. Because
essentially, the smaller optical flow for
vectors correspond of large Z. And we'll
be able to figure this out exactly
mathematically in a few slides. [sound] So
let me tell you the outline of what we
will do in the, in the next few slides. So
first of all we are going to derive an
equation which relates the optical flow
field to the scene depth and the motion of
the camera. So this is the fundamental
equation of optical flow. And we will do
this by simple geometrical analysis and
this analysis will exploit the
representation of, of rigid body motion as
some combination of translation and
rotation. That's after we have done that
we are gonna to try to make sense of this.
We are gonna to try to interpret this and
get some physical [inaudible]. And
basically what we will find is that the
transitional component of the optical flow
is the more important one. And that
reveals something about Z, the depth, as
well as the transitional vector T. The
rotation of the component of the flow
field is, also important but, less so. Its
main purpose is to tell us something about
commotion. It tells us about how the
camera is rotating. It doesn't tell us
anything about the scene. So we'll try to
understand that as well. It will fall out,
more or less, straightforwardly from the
equations. So let's get down to business.
Our goal is going to be to derive the
equation which relates the optical flow
field to see in depth, Z affects Y, and
the motion of the camera T omega. Okay, so
let's get going. How does the point X, and
note that I always use upper case
quantities for scene variables, how does
the point X in the scene move? So let's
we're gonna give the movement to the
camera. So assume that the camera has a
translational velocity which has three
components [inaudible] X, [inaudible] Y. T
sub y, t sub z, and an angular velocity,
which is given by the components of omega.
How do I characterize the movement of a po
int in the scene? The movement of a point
in the scene is equal and opposite to the
movement of the camera. So the camera's
movement is given by t And omega. So in
the scene, so points in the scene will
appear to move equal and opposite. So
that, so we have a translational term and
a rotational term given here and the minus
signs are because the camera is moving and
we consider movement of some point in the
scene and x dot here is essentially the
standard notation for Temporal derivative,
where X is a vector. Dx upon dt is given
by X dot. Okay, so once we have this
vector equation, 3.1 in this notation. I
can write it out in coordinates, and, this
is just working out this vector product.
And if you do that, you should get this
expression. So this is quite
straightforward, and now we have expressed
the moment of a point in the scene. In
terms of how the x coordinates changes,
how the y coordinate changes, and how the
z coordinate changes using the information
about The transitional vector, and here,
this, this X, y, and Z correspond to sort
of the scene coordinates. Okay. I should
perhaps have used upper-case for X, Y and
Z here, because these are meant to be
scene coordinates. Okay, so now we are
going to consider the effect of
projection. So far in fact we had no
notion of perspective projection. It was
just some ob, the camera is some object
moving, and then we had, we had described
relative movement as a combination of
translation and rotation. So the equations
of perspective projections are given here.
So the only little trick here is that, I
assume F=1, this is not a big deal. I, I
am just saying that instead of measuring
in centimeters or meters, I measured it in
measure length in units of focal length.
This is a kind of trick physicists use all
the time. If you, if I want too, I could
actually have the f in there and get it
through the equations. In any case, it's
not a big deal. So what we have to do is
to take the derivative. So if I have
little x equals upper-case X upon Z, I
have to now take the deriv ative of the
circumspect to time. So now we have the
standard formula. So, how do I take the
derivative of a fraction where X is the
numerator and Z is the denominator? Well,
we take the, the denominator gets squared
and we get X dot Z, minus Z dot X. This is
standard Calculus, right, calculus for the
derivative of the ratio of two functions.
So that's what will give us this
expression right here and I'll get a
similar expression for why not. So this is
totally straight forward. So this just a
consequence of calculus, we are
considering how the little x, how the
image plain projection little x and image
plain projection little y, how that
changes when, when I over time. And these
here I should really have, uppercase Y and
Z should have been used. So this is a
error in my slide. I used lower case
quantities here but they should all have
been upper case, because these are seen
quantities. >> Okay. >> So let's move
right along. So now what we have to do is
to plug in, expressions for the temporal
derivatives of X and Y and so forth, from,
from the expression here. So that's what I
do. So I take. So I, let's say I take this
equation, and then x dot. I plug in x-dot
from here, and I plug in z-dot from here,
and, that will give me, little x-dot, and
then I can simplify a little bit using
that fact that little x is x over z, and
little y is y over z. So I'm going to not
go through the algebra for you here, but
you should sit down and verify it, and you
should be able to work out this equation,
so please...very farthest, It's just
calculation, but it's worth doing. So we
have now got an expression. This is the
grand equations that I'm interested in.
And I'm going to rewrite it so you can see
this. Let's keep, get the [inaudible]
right again. So what is X dot and Y dot?
So this is, as always X dot means d sub X
upon d T and Y dot means d Y upon d T. So
these are the two components of optical
flow, respectively the X component and Y
component. And what we did over the
previous slide was to derive relationship
between thes e guys and movement in the
scene. And the movement in the scene has a
translation component And a rotation
component. And then we have little x,
little y, these are just coordinates
[inaudible]. And, then we have this
fellow, Z, and Z is in general, actually
going to be a function of little x and
little y. And this is, of course, depth in
the scene. So what do we observe? We
observe that the translational component
has, has a dependence on that. So this sky
is going to tell us something about seeing
death. The rotation component has no
dependence on Z. So, what the rotation
component does is, it just tells us about
rotation.