Okay, welcome back. So in the last
lecture, we derived the equations for
optical flow. In this lecture we're going
to study them in greater depth, and show
what use they provide us for computer
vision, or, in fact, any biological vision
system. So let me begin by reminding you
of the equations which we derived last
time. These were shown last time, and the
way to understand. These, is that there is
a transitional component and a rotation
component. I want to make one bit of
notation clear. These, these are vector
equations, so they are, I've kind of
written them out in a compact way, But
These are two vector equations, which
really consist of the two, two scalar
equations. So in fact, if I take this,
This, this matrix vector multiplication,
and I can read out. I will get two rows.
And similarly I will get two rows here,
and these are also two rows. So if we
consider the first row, I will, that
corresponds to the equation for X start,
and the bottom row corresponds to the
equation for Y dot. So just to make clear
that I have expressed in a compact way
using vector notation what really are two
separate equations, one for the X
component of the optical flow, and one for
the Y component of the optical flow. So
let's go, going and first we'll concern
ourselves with the transitional component
on this red stuff here. So, what's the
optical flow pure translation? If the
motion is purely translation we can ignore
the rotational component because the omega
is a, a zero. Omega x omega by omega Z a
zero, and then the flow field is given by
these two expressions, this is just from
the previous slide, just substitute
omega=0. Okay, I want to get some
intuition about this, how am I going to do
this? Because just leaving this as formula
is, is, doesn't give us proper
understanding, So we're going to gain
intuition by considering this special case
of translation along the optical axis. So
what's this special case? So this is, this
translation, but the translation is along
the z axis. So imagine that there is a
camera moving. But its movement is just
movement along the z axis. There is no
movement along x and y. There is no
rotation. So imagine that you're just
looking straight ahead, and you're walking
in the direction in which you're looking.
Right? This is what most of us should do
most of the time. What does the flow field
become? We can start with the expressions
here, and we can substitute that t sub X,
and t sub Y as zero. So we get the
expressions shown here for the X component
of the optical flow U, and the Y component
of the optical flow. And let me do my
standard trick of writing these two scalar
equations as one vector equation and
that's what I do here. So this U, V
transposed really means little U, little V
as a vector, and this X, Y transposed as X
and Y as a vector. So these are column
vectors, and here these are row vectors,
which have been transposed with a letter T
[sound]. Okay. [sound]. So we get a fairly
simple looking expression. So the optical
flow vector is proportional to the
position vector x, y, and the
proportionality factor is tz upon z. Let's
see if we can plot this out. Okay, so I
repeat. Uv is, is, UV the optical flow
vector, the optical flow vector here, this
is the position vector and the
proportionality constant is TZ upon Z.
This diagram shows what the optical flow
field looks like in this case. So first of
all, what happens when we are at the
origin? So the origin here, So at the
origin x=0, y=0. So the optical flow must
be zero. Uv must be 0,0 And the origin. So
that's shown here, by the, this is the
origin of the image plane. And at the
origin what we should have is the optical
flow vectors are of length zero. The
optical flow vector is a scalar multiple
of the position vector. This has a very
simple meaning. This means that all, if I
have a point. X, Y So there is,
essentially, the position vector which is
drawn here in blue. The optical flow
vector at the location XY is in the same
direction, scaled by some factor, and that
sca-, factor is TZ upon Z. And but it
points in the s-, in the direction of, the
position vector XY. So this means that,
all the, the optical flow, so, at this
location here, XY. The position vector is
going to be like this. So the optical flow
vector is in, a scaled copy of that, The
scaling factor being given by TZ upon Z.
So the optical flow pattern has this very
beautiful starburst like Pattern to it.
All these vectors appear to be streaming
out; actually they are streaming out when
we are approaching an object. So imagine
that I am driving, and I am driving
headlong towards a wall. So the wall is
ahead of me at ten meters. Its Z is
constant at ten meters, and I'm driving
towards it. Well, I hope I'll break at
some point, but before I do, I see this
optical flow pattern, which is all these
arrows streaming out. Okay. What will
happen if I was? Reverse in the car, if I
was driving back. Well, at that point what
will happen is that the sign of TZ will,
will flip. So all these vectors, instead
of pointing outwards would be pointing
inwards. So when I'm driving towards a
wall, the optical flow is streaming
outwards. When I'm driving away from a
wall, I, I'm reversing from a wall, the
optical flow vectors will be streaming
inwards. And this proportional artifact is
TZ upon Z. So that's, that's a very nice
property of the optical flow field. The
lengths of these vectors are proportional
to TZ upon Z, and let's try to get a
better understanding of that. Okay, there
is one little problem which confronts us
in our, in our analysis of the optical
flow-field corresponding to pure
translation. So the, the, this property is
called the Scale Factor Ambiguity. So
imagine that I took the... The world, and
I made the world K times bigger, and I
made mov, my movement K times faster. So I
made the world Z becomes KZ. So imagine
that everything in the world is twice as
big, and I move twice as fast. What'll
happen to the optical flow? Since TZ upon
Z, that ratio is not going to be changed;
the optical flow field will be exactly the
same. So this is something we have known
how to exploit for quite s ome time.
People in the movie making business can
make these tiny toy sets with a tiny
Godzilla and a tiny building. And then
they have, they can move the camera only a
little bit, but the optical flow may be
the same as if you had a fast moving
camera and a larger world. So the optical
flow vector is unchanged. This tells us
that we have no hope of recovering the
absolute. Speed TZ or the absolute depth
Z. So in a sense this is bad news because
our goal was to use the optical field,
flow field to tell us something about
depth in the scene. And there is no way
out. There is no way to recover absolute
depth in meters and absolute speed in
meters per second. But there is one little
important thing we can do, In fact the
most important thing with respect to
navigation. I want you to tell me what Z
upon TZ is. So the units of z, z is a
distance In meters. D sub z is a speed In
meters/ second. Okay. What is this ratio
tell me? This ratio is, so imagine there
is a wall at a distance of Z and I am
going at speed t/Z directly towards it.
Well Z upon tZ is the time to collision.
So you can work out that the units of this
are in seconds. So z upon tz is, is in how
many seconds am I going to collide with
the wall. So, and here the scale factor
ambiguity doesn't come into play because.
It could be that the z is in kilometers,
and t sub z is in kilometers per second,
or z is in meters and tz is in meters per
second. It's the ratio that matters. If
you're moving faster, but the world is, is
bigger, it will take you the same time to
collision, or time to contact. So, the
important point is that this
proportionality factor tells us about the
time to collision. And now, here is a bit
of advice. If you are driving towards a
wall just keep the time to contact
positive. That will keep you out of
trouble. So, in fact, this advice seems to
be followed by insects and bugs and so on
and so forth. There have been quite a few
experiments done by biologists, which
demonstrate that time to contact is a very
valuable variable, which is in f act used.
So, what you do is, you can control
essentially breaking behavior, by making
down decrees as, as appropriate as, okay.
I'm not gonna get, get into the details of
those studies. But The beautiful result is
that from the optical flow field we can
determine time to contact, which is in
fact the variable we want to use for
controlling our braking behavior, so as to
avoid colliding with obstacles. Let me now
turn to the case of general translation. I
did, now the bush, the baby case
corresponding to translation along the
optical axis. What happens when we
consider a general translation? So we have
a piece of X, a piece of Y, and a piece of
Z. So to work this out, let's start with
the figuring out when is the optical flow
00. So in the previous case the optical
flow is zero at the origin. In this case
the optical flow will be zero at the
following points. Let's figure out. When
the X component of optical flow is zero,
minus X plus minus T sub X plus X T sub Z
equals zero. X should be equal to T sub X
upon T sub Z. Minus T sub Y plus Y T sub Z
should be zero which implies that Y equals
T sub Y upon T sub Z. What this tells me
is, if I consider the point. Tx upon TC,
Ts of Y on Ts of Z, at this location the
optical flow. Uv is 0,0. So, this point Tx
upon tz, ty upon tz is the moral
equivalent of the origin in the previous
case. We will call this point. The focus
of expansion And, let me do a little
calculation to show why this term is
appropriate. What we should do is, let's
take the optical flow fee, but let's do a
change of coordinates. So, imagine that
instead of taking the standard origin,
which is zero, zero. Let's consider a new
origin, and let's make the new origin at
the point TX upon TZ And TY upon
[inaudible]. So therefore, we have changed
coordinates from X to X prime, and Y to Y
prime by just a simple shift. So in this
diagram, I have XY, which is the standard
coordinate system. And then I have a new
coordinate system for X prime, Y prime. So
the optical flow field in the
neo-coordinate system. So let's go back to
the expression here. So, here we have the
optical flow field in the XY coordinate
system, and instead we want to write it
out in the X prime Y prime coordinate
system. And we'll do a change of color,
origin from XY to X prime Y prime, and
rewrite these expressions in the X prime Y
prime coordinate system. Again, I leave
you to work this out, but if you do that,
you are going to get an expression which
now looks very simple. It is that uv. In
the x prime, y prime coordinate system has
the simple tz upon z. X prime, Y prime. So
we again get this scale factor
relationship. That we saw in the, the easy
case, but now we have to refer everything
to a new coordinates system at TX upon TC,
TY upon TC. So the, we'll call this TX
upon TC at, at, TY upon TC to be F, the
F-foy, [sound] F-foy is how we abbreviate
it but this corresponds to the focus of
expansion [sound]. And why do we use the
stub? Recall that in the, in the case of
translation along the Z axis, the optical
flow vectors appeared to stream outwards
from the origin, and we could call the
origin the focus of expansion, because
that's the point from which all these
vectors appear to be streaming outwards.
Here, these vectors will be streaming out
with respect to the point TX upon TZ, TY
upon TZ. So these are the coordinates of
the focus of expansion. So in a sense if I
have an optical flow field all I have to
do is look and it corresponds to peer
translation. There will be a point at
which the flow field is zero at which the
flow is zero and all the vectors will
appear to be streaming out from there.
That is the focus of expansion. And the
focus of expansion directly tells me about
the direction of translation, because it,
the coordinates of the focus of expansion
give me tx upon tz, ty upon tz. So this
basically is information about the
translation vector t. It does not have
absolute information about the magnitude
of DX comma DY comma DZ. But we can never
get hope to get that because of the scale
factor ambiguity. All we can hope to do is
to r ecover the direction of transmission.
And the location of the focus of expansion
gives us exactly that. [sound]. So, now we
have understood the case of translation,
Which is which is beautiful Because the
case of translation. It shows us that we
cannot recover the absolute velocity of
translation. We can recover the time to
collision; we can recover the direction
the direction of translation. Of course,
in the general case we don't just have
translation, we also have rotation. So
this rotation component is, is described
here. This is the rotation component. So I
could. Spend a few slides on trying to
understand the rotation component. So
imagine that there is no translation at
all, the camera is just rotating. Well. I
can do that, but there is really not that
much insight there. It's kind of boring.
If you move the, if you rotate the camera,
well the ball will appear to rotate. But
it tells you nothing whatsoever about the,
the distance of objects in the world
Because if you see this expression, Z does
not figure. It only depends on image plane
coordinates with X and Y, which we know.
And. The omega vector, omega x, omega y,
omega z, So therefore the flow field, the
rotational flow field will tell us what's,
hap, how we are rotating. So it will tell
us information about omega. It won't tell
us anything about the C. So, so here is a
straightforward story. Now, if we have
translation and rotation going on at the
same time, then algorithmitically we do
have a challenge of trying to separate the
translational and rotational components. A
number of algorithms have been developed
for that, but I won't get into the details
of that. What I'm gonna do know, is to
just show you some pictures of the flow
fields and how they reveal information
about the scene. [sound]. So here's an
example. This is what the flow field looks
like if I'm translating along the Z axis
towards a wall edge. So there is a focus
of expansion, which is at the origin. All
these vectors are streaming out because
I'm driving towards the wall. And that' s
about it. It's, there's a focus of
expansion is at the origin. And we have
information in the lengths of these
vectors about the time to contact. Okay,
this is what the optical flow looks like
for points on a road. So here I'm
imagining that I'm driving on a road and
so the upper half of the image plane is
the sky. The lower half of the image plane
is the, the ground. There is a horizon
here if you like and the optical flow
vectors are, are, so here the Z varies. So
since the Z varies, these are nearer
points. And these are points essentially
at infinity. These are far points. So,
recall that in the optical flow
translational component there is a one
upon z factor, so when z is at infinity,
the optical flow has to be zero. And when
points are nearer, the optical flow is
larger. So this is what the flow looks
like on the road. And, you can have a
chance to experience this, particularly
when you're driving after it has rained.
So the, the water on the, water drops on
the road surface, they enable you to sense
the optical flow more vividly, and you
will exactly perceive these vectors.
Another way to think about this is that.
The focus of expansion is really the
vanishing point corresponding to the, the
vector of translation, because when I'm
driving. Every point in the road is moving
with velocity minus T. So these are all
vectors, and these are all parallel to
each other. So there must be a vanishing
point of this family of parallel lines.
And what is that vanishing point? That is
the focus of expansion. So the focus of
expansion is, really, just the vanishing
point that we studied earlier in disguise.
Okay. This is the truly boding case. So
imagine that, I am translating along the
X-axis in front of a wall. So I am just
moving the camera to the side, the wall
that's in some fixed distance. Nothing
changes. The optical flow is as boding as
you get. Okay, here is the optical flow
field when you keep rotating the camera
about its axis. So you get this rotational
pattern, it tells us what you are doing to
the camer A. It doesn't tell us anything
about whether the wall is near or far, or
whether we are going to collide with it in
five seconds or 5,000 seconds. Here's an
interesting case. This is rotating about
the Y axes which giving the coordinates
system we like to use in camera's is, is
vertical. So when you rotating about the y
axis this is what the flow field will look
like. Let me conclude by talking about the
importance of optical flow. The big idea
that I want you to take away from these
last few lectures is that, suppose an
animal or a robot could analyze its radio
signal, and measure the optical flow
field. It could use this data to compute
depth and [inaudible] motion depth, Z
affects Y And ego motion which is the
translational and rotational velocity. You
may not get exactly the Z or exactly the
T, you may, you may get some ratios of
that but that is good enough for
controlling your movement. There is a fair
amount of evidence from perceptual and
neuroscience studies that animals in fact
have both the ability to measure optical
flow. So this is required so there is some
neural hardware that is needed to measure
optical flow given the imagine of the
function of time. Given the video data And
That, given that we have computed the
optical flow. Given that we have measured
the optical flow. Can we use it, to
control. A moment, avoid obstacles, et
cetera, and flies use it, diving birds use
it. Many, many animals use it, and we
could use it for robots. There is in this
whole enterprise this req, requirement
that we must have a way of computing the
optical flow field given reduced signal.
And I have not told you how to do that.
This requires work; it's not trivial
because essentially to measure the optical
flow we need a way to know what are
corresponding points over time. So if
there is a location XY in one time frame
and then I say that this point has moved
to x+delta, x comma y+delta y. I need a
way to say that this is that there is a
notion of corresponding points over time.
And this requires an algorithm and some
computation. We are going to study that
later. For now I've just shown you how, if
we could measure the optical f, flow field
we could use it for a number of useful
Applications. Thank you.