Hello. Welcome to the course on computer
vision. My name is Jitendra Malik, and I'm
in the Department of EECS at UC Berkeley.
So, let's begin with the beginning.
A camera creates an image of the external
world. And computer vision is the science
and engineering discipline which is
concerned with making inferences about
this external world, given one or more
of its images. I mean the part about
science and engineering. Science comes in
because there are fundamental principles
associated with the physics of image
formation, And statistical regularities in
the external world which makes this
enterprise at all possible.
It's engineering because there are many, many
practical applications of what we'll study
in this course. And we'll get to see some
of them. Let's begin with what's in an
image. So here's this image, and you might
look at it and say there's a tiger and
grass. But what does a computer program
see? For the computer program, it's just a
bunch of pixels. And they have some
values, some RGB values, and here's
another window and there are some other
RGB values. The only way we get any
meaning out of this is by the activity of
the brain. It's the humans that perceive
structure in it, otherwise you just have
an area of values. The goal in computer
vision is to give computers the same
capability. So in a grand sense, our goal
is to go from pixels to perception. So
let's being with this image, What can we
do with this image? One of the things we
can do is to divide up the image into
various regions. So here I marked out the
region, colors pointing to the tiger. I
can describe that region. I can say it's
orange. I can say that it has some texture
stripes in it. We can go further. We can
attach some semantic labels. We can say
there's water, grass, tigers, sun and so
on. We can continue this process further,
not only can we label the tiger, but we
can label parts of the tiger. Such as its
back, head, eye, mouth and so on. So this
is what we humans can perceive in an
image, and the goal of computer vision is
to achieve something similar to this. Once
a upon a time we had a very feet forward
processing view of vision and there were
various theories and models constructed in
which we started out by analyzing local
neighborhoods of an image. We moved on
from that to analyzing the surfaces and
contours of the object. So we are, I'm
trying to show here the surfaces
corresponding to the tiger. The grass,
water, and so on. And then, finally, we
went to high level inferences about
scenes, and the objects and the scenes.
Each of these stages of processing had
natural techniques that could be
associated with them. For example, if
you're analyzing neighborhoods of images,
then image processing is the canonical
technique to be used, Linear filtering,
convolution, and so on. When we try to
analyze the image of the levels of
contours and surfaces, that's what is
called mid level vision. And here is where
we have grouping operations, and
inferences about figure ground, and the
surface attributes of the scene. And
finally we get to high level vision, where
recognition is the main, goal. And, this
is where one draws on statistical
techniques such as, pattern recognition,
classification, etc. So this feet forward
view of vision is regarded as rather
simplistic these days. The way we think
about it now is that we think that vision
has three interconnected processes. One of
these is recognition of objects and
activities. So, giving objects names like,
tiger, grass, and so on. Another process
is the one of reorganization, or sometimes
it's called grouping and segmentation.
This involves inferences such as this set
of pixels belong together to
one object. And then, we have
reconstructing 3D structure. By that, we
mean, recovering depths of objects in the
scene, how far away various objects are
with respect to the camera. So that's the
third process. And all these processes
interrelate. So, the results of
recognition can help with reconstruction,
the results of reconstruction can help
with recogniti on, and so on and so forth.
So let's start talking about the state of
the art of in recognition. One of the
earliest problems that was tackled in
computer vision was that of 110 digit
recognition. And there are some standard
data sets, one called MNEST, one called
USBS, and you can search for these on the
Web. And we are by now pretty good at this
problem. So, one of the pioneers in this
area is Gam Lakun, and he has developed
radius theorem and network architectures,
For this problem. And, he has shown that
these architectures can give Error rates
as low as on the order of half a percent
on these data sets. And the resulting
systems are quite faster, and these can be
used in practice, and are being used in
practice for check reading and so on.
There are a number of different methods
out there which manage to achieve this.
I'd mentioned, like to mention randomized
decision trees, because of [inaudible]
what is used in, some of the, the work on
figuring out. Body parts in the algorithm
used in the connect system for example,
Under the rubric of random forests. So
moving right along, there are other
problems we can do quite well at. For
example, you've all encountered captures,
these distorted text, that you have to
figure out what the text is to get a free
email account, or get access to some
website, and so. Earlier line of work that
we did some time ago that showed that
these Can in fact be recognized by
computer programs. So maybe standard OCR
programs can't do this job, but the most
advanced computer vision techniques can do
a perfectly good job at identifying the
words even though they are in messed up
background or distorted in some way. So,
let's talk a bit about general object
category recognition. Humans can recognize
that all of these are faces even though
they look quite different from each other.
Or that all of these are flowers even the,
though they look different from each
other. And this is one of the fundamental
capabilities that we wish to give computer
region systems. So one of the classic data
sets in this Was collected at Cal Tech,
and it's called the Cal Tech 101 data set.
And this was collected by Fifi and Perona
back in 2004. So what they did was to
collect examples from the web of images of
101 different categories, and these could
include pianos, dogs, cats, faces, and so
forth. And for each of these categories
they collected something like 30 to 300
images. The images themselves were rather
simple. They had typically just one object
in the centre of the image. But the
question was, would computer programs be
able to find which of these and then what
different categories that object was. And,
And this was a challenge now thrown open
to the entire computer vision community.
And what I'm showing you here are some
curves which are performance curves where
on the Y axis we're, there is some measure
of performance, which is, What percentage
of the object were classified correctly?
And on the X axis here are examples. How
many examples were used? So, for now you
can focus on just one vertical column
corresponding to fifteen training
examples. So, what's interesting is that
when the data-set first came out,
performance was at about sixteen percent
correct. In a sense that's terrible. That
means that 84 percent of the time the
program was wrong. But a positive way to
think about it is that if we were just
performing a chance, performance would be
just one Percent. So sixteen percent was
significantly better than chance. What's
very interesting is that in three years,
due to the efforts of many different
groups, performance went up from sixteen
percent to 65 percent correct. Which is a
factor of four improvement and
performance. This is fantastic, this an
indication of a field that is finally
getting its act together. And, today we
don't work that much on its data set
anymore, because we prefer data sets where
there will be multiple objects in the
scene. But, this was a good indicator that
the field was making progress and
recognition. So I will give you an example
of what kinds of data sets are popular
these days, The so called Pascal visual
object challenge. And this has been the
dominant data set in the field for the
last five years. And this has much more
complex scenes. As you can see in these
images, you typically have multiple
objects. In an images, for example this
image you see a TV monitor, and a person,
and a keyboard, and so on an so forth. In
this image you have a sheep and the
presence of Grass and the goal of this
challenge was to test whether we could do
recognition in these more difficult
circumstances. In these more difficult
circumstances the goal was we should be
able to mark That A bounding box
corresponding to the object. So somehow
you can mark the position of the sheep, or
the position of the dog. And the way we
mark these is by drawing a bounding box.
And when I say we, I really mean the
computer program. And the way we judge
performance here is by, so called
precision recall curves. And you'll
encounter this repeatedly in the, in the
course. So precision is measured here on
the X, on the, on the Y axis. And, let me
use a. So precision here is on the Y axis.
So precision means what percentage of the
objects that, computer program declared
were bicycles were actually bicycles. So
ideally, you want precision to be one. And
then, we also measure recall. Recall is,
how many of the bicycles in the data set
did we manage to find? And of course you
would ideally want the recall to be one,
and position to be one. In practice, we
are not so lucky. And so what happens is
that there is some threshold parameter,
and if we have a more lax threshold, you
get high recall. If you get more strict
threshold, you have high precision. And
typically you get a curve, as shown here.
By varying the threshold, and the
threshold here is being made more lax, and
as a result you increase recall and lower
precision. So the ideal point, of course,
would be a precision recall of one, as I
have marked here. And different algorithms
have different curves, and those are
shown here. And you can get to these
curves by searching for Pascal VOC on
the web. And the area under this curve
becomes a measure of the technique. And
ideal curve would have an area under the
curve of one. But in practice, we get
areas such as 55.3 percent, or 54.3%. So
in a certain sense, these numbers which
are close to 50 percent tell us that we
are sort of halfway through solving this
problem of detection of bicycles. Let's
move along to analysis of images of
people. People are some of, one of the
most difficult categories to analyze.
Just, if you look at this image, you will
see the variety in appearance, due to
clothing, due to pose, due to occlusion,
and so on and so forth. And yet, people
are a very important category because if
we can analyze images of people, there are
a variety of applications that will become
accessible to us. So. I'll give you an
example. Even from single images, just the
pose and appearance of a person can tell
you whether a person is falling or running
or walking or riding a horse. And, in
fact, computer programs are able to do
this. Let me look at, look at actions more
generally. So there are a variety of
actions that we are interested in. Some of
these actions correspond to movement and
posture change. So, these are examples,
run walk, crawl. In fact you can think of
actions as English words, and objects as
nouns. A large class of actions have to do
with object manipulation. So, these
include the examples here. Pick an object,
carry an object, hold an object, lift an
object, and so on. And we would like to
able to describe what's happening in an
image by using these terms. So, of course,
actions include, conversational gesture. I
mean, in this example, suppose I move my
hands about. That's conversational
gesture. And of course, sign language.
Recognition is not limited to objects and
actions. We might be, we are able to
recognize materials. So in this example,
looking at this image, you might be able
to guess what the material. Is it felt,
polyester, rough plaster, leather,
concrete, and so on. And in computer
vision we seek to develop techniques for
recognizing materials. So let's return to
the central problems of vision. I've spent
a lot of time talking about the different
sub-aspects of the problem of recognition
of objects in activities. Lets turn now to
reorganization. So the task of organizing
an image from pixels into objects. So here
are some examples, segmentations from the
work of segmentation data set. What we did
was we took images, such as shown here in
the left column. And for each of these
images what we did was we asked various
human subjects to look at these images and
to mark out the objects in them. And what
you see are different people's.
Segmentations of these images. But what
you see clearly is that people are able to
mark the objects. So if you look at this
example, they can clearly mark the two
worlds. In some, some. Humans are more
detailed. They mark out all the object,
and the parts of objects, and some will do
less. It's clear that we have this
capability of marking out the set of
pixels which correspond to a single
object. This is an ability that we wish to
have computer programs replicate. Here are
more examples. So, this, I like this
example of the butterfly on a, on a tree.
Because, examples of objects against the
natural background really challenge,
segmentation systems. Because objects
evolve animals evolve camouflage so that
they can be hidden against their
background. And that makes the task of
detecting them against those backgrounds
particularly challenging. So you can see
that in these examples. So how do we do
this? Of course we're gonna spend some
time on this but there are a number of, so
let's look at, take a concrete example. So
here is this, this, this wooden bed stand.
I, then, here is the vegan correspondent
to the bedspread. And how do we find the
boundaries between these? We can find the
boundaries with a number of low-level
cues, such as brightness in color, one is
green, one is beige, the te xture. This is
a single image, if we had, if we had a
moving camera then the nearer object would
move faster, and that would give you a
cue. Binocular disparity if we had two
eyes. Looking at this scene and there,
there, then again, we have acute to depth.
And finally of course we can use familiar
configuration, we can segment out a face
from the background once we have
recognized that those pixels correspond to
a face. So we'll have an opportunity to
study these variety of techniques later in
the course. Okay, so now I've done to the
third fundamental problem of vision which
is that of reconstructing 3D structure.
How do we do this? It's very helpful to
think about reconstruction as the inverse
problem of computer graphics. So computer
graphics is the forward problem. What
graphics people are able to do is, given
that scene geometry. By that, I mean
the layout of the different objects,
models of the surfaces [inaudible] on the
scene, and so on. As well as the
reflectance properties, The color. That,
the, in a more general case it's called a
bidirectional reflectance distribution
function, and of course the position and
distribution of the light sources. Given
this, we can simulate the physics. We
simulate the physics of light transport,
and we produce an image. That's what
computer graphics does. Computer vision in
a certain sense is the inverse problem. We
are given an image, and we want to
deconstruct what is the scene that gave
rise to this image. So they can of course
be multiple images, and, and if we are
lucky. But our goal is to recover scene
geometry, the reflectances of the various
objects in the scene, as well as the scene
illuminations. So, How do I do this.
Recovery of geometry has historical roots
in photo geometry and the analysis of 3D
Q's in human vision. But it's worth noting
that it can be done. Even with single
images if we have some knowledge of the
object class. And I'll give you an example
of that. Multiple images make the problem
easier. But it's not trivial, as co
rresponding points must be identified.
Once you have found corresponding points
than we can draw on triangulation. Of
course there are settings when you have an
active camera, such as for example in the
Kinect, where you project a pattern on the
image and that ability to predict a
pattern gives you, an easy way to solve
the correspondence problem. So let's take
up some examples. So, here's an example
from human vision, where binoculars
stereopsis can be used. We have two
different eyes. They give you slightly
different images of the scene, and the
difference between those two images is
related to the depth of objects in the
scene. So that's one thing we can do. But
of course we could use multiple views. So
here's an example of, 3D models that were
constructed of Berkeley campus. This is
from a project going back nearly fifteen
years, led by Paul Debevec. And what
they did was that they took a number of
examples, a number of images of the
leading buildings, such as this clock
tower. And, surrounding buildings on,
campus. Some of these pictures were taken
with cameras on a kite. And from these
multiple pictures 3D models could be
constructed. And this is of course now
standard technology and it's embodied in a
number of different commercial products.
But here's an interesting example. With,
extra assumptions even one images suffices. So
here's a reconstruction of the 3D geometry
of the Taj Mahal. The Taj Mahal happens to
be a very symmetric figure, and therefore,
even in a single image, you get the
equivalent of multiple views. And one can,
in fact, reconstruct the three dimensional
shape of this object. Because an example
of. Where we do not know what is the
object, but somehow when we look at this,
this tablet or whatever they have this
perception that there must be some groves
and there must be some ridges and so on. I
clearly hear it all the information is
being carried by the pattern of light and
dark. What's worth noting is that these
two images that you see here are really.
Essent ially the same image, it's just
that one is a, one has been rotated by 180
degrees. And that rotation by 180 degrees
is enough to change your perception. In
one case, what you saw as ridges, now you
see as grooves. And why is that?
Well, that has to do with
assumptions that the visual system makes about the
position of light sources. So in the
environment that we grew up in, the light
comes from the sun and the sun is above.
So there is going to be a certain pattern
Of shading associated with the ridge, and
essentially when you flip... rotate the image by 180
degrees that assumption causes us to
assume that the... now instead of looking at the ridge,
you're looking at the groove.
Of course we can make
inferences about spatial layout, not just
the shape of a single object. And this is
a kind of scene which is very common in
Renaissance paintings, which showed these
courtyards which were full of rectangular
slabs. And we are making a number of
assumptions here. We assume that the slabs
are of the same size and shape in the
scene. But they look different in the
image because some are nearer to you and
some are farther to you, away from you.
This enables us to guess how far away and
at what orientation these objects are.
Again, the big picture is the following.
Even when we have a single image, we are
able to categorize The objects in, in
terms of depth. We can say some object is
in front of some other object. So in this
kind of an example, this simple line
drawing example, we can say that R1
appears in front of R2 and R2 appears in
front of R3. And this we can do even with
a single image. Of course if we have
multiple images such as in the case of
stereopsis then we will use that
information to recover what objects are,
are nearer to you and which objects are
farther away. What is all this for? In a
certain sense we can ask this fundamental
question. Why do we try to recover
properties of the external world? And it's
helpful here to think about biology. In
biology, why did vision evolve? Vision
evolved because it gave the organism
which had vision some gain, some benefit.
It had to give it some benefit in terms of
being able to find food, or to avoid becoming food.
So, vision always is associated
with that ability to act in the
world. And here, two examples of actions;
One is locomotion. You can move about and
in which vision enables you to work with
maps of the environment,
based on your previous experience and when you are
walking about you can avoid obstacles.
Vision also allows you to manipulate objects. You
can grasp objects. You can pick and
place objects. You can use tools. So,
these are all. Examples of hand eye
coordination where the hand together with
the eye is used to perform action in the
world. This is very important because
just. From an evolutionary point of view,
a visual system which did not help with
action would not be of much use and
clearly would not have any evolutionary
advantage that would create favorable
selection pressure. So finally let's turn
to the application of computer vision.
There are many, many examples, and pretty
much these examples, have, at this point
do not require that we construct a full
vision system comparable to a human being,
but we construct some aspect of this
ability and that's enough for us to
construct useful applications. For example
I have some here; Biometrics, identifying
people. So, for example, you want to
control access to some environment, and
you do it by doing face recognition.
Computational photography, this is a
emerging discipline over the last 10-15
years. And essentially, the idea is that
we can attach a computer to the camera,
and then we are no longer stuck with the
passive image captured. We can choose the,
the imaging parameters of the camera to
construct better images. Very simple
example is that nowadays when we take
photographs of when there is some program
which is trying to detect faces.
And.. unable... and what is done with that is
to make sure that the faces
are in focus. Because the expectation is
that when we take images, we really want
the people's faces to be in sharp focus.
Human computer interaction is a leading
application, because, with the help of a
camera, you can, determine the pulse of
the human body. And of course, one of the
leading examples of this is the Microsoft
Kinect system which is used in gaming. We
can create three dimensional virtual
worlds by variations of the techniques
that I talked about earlier for 3D
reconstruction. And, again, this is a very
widespread, Technology now, Content-based
image retrieval. I mean, when you do web
searches, and you want to find examples of
images of certain categories. Sometimes
you can do it based on text, but sometimes
you can also explore image content, and
many, many more. I will not. Continue with
these, this list of examples here. But a
comprehensive list can be found at a
website which is maintained by Derek Law.
And I recommend you to go, check this
website for hundreds of examples of
companies which have computer vision products.
You wouldn't have noticed that
in this lecture I've jumped back and forth
between talking about human vision
and computer vision. And to me, this
is, there is a lot to be learned from
human vision. And Let's try to get
in, a bit into how and why. So, human
vision is studied by many different
scientists. So, perception is a
traditional discipline, typically studied
my psychologists. And here, we consider
the visual system as a black box. We are
trying to figure out what a human would
perceive in an image, and try to construct
a scientific theory for that. Neuroscience
of course gets into the black box, and
it's trying to understand what are the
brain areas associated with, with vision.
And vision of course starts in the retina
but goes on in the brain. What's
interesting is that something like 30 to
50 percent of the brain is devoted to
visual processing. Finally, there is an
understanding of vision at the functional
level, which has to do with how the laws
of optics and the statistics of the world
we live in. Make certain interpretation of
an image much more likely. Now this
version of the problem is equally. Valid
for a human system as well as for a
computer vision system. We are. Both the,
both humans and computer vision systems
are equally constrained by the laws of
optics, and the statistics of the world we
live in. So at the functional level,
there's going to be a very good match.
Perception and neuroscience we do not need
to copy exactly. But often. It has turned
out that both studies of, of human vision
and psychology and neuroscience has been a
source of wonderful inspiration for
computer vision systems. So I'll give you
another example of, the use of, of the
functional level. This is not to do with
vision but flight. When we consider birds
and airplanes, we don't build airplanes by
imitating wings with feathers and bones
and muscles and so on. How are the basic
principles of flight, the basic principles
of lift. Using Bernoulli's principle has
to be the same when we consider birds or.
Happenings. And what we are trying to
uncover are the counterparts of
Bernoulli's principle. That's the science
of vision. And, those are going to be the
same when we, whether we study human
vision or computer vision. I should take
you a little bit through the history of
computer vision. It's a relatively young
discipline. It, it's like any field of
computer science. It's more or less 50
years old. We say, I, I picked this 1963
as a specific year, because this is the,
the, the year when the first PHD thesis in
computer vision, is, was written. And the
beginnings of the field were in artificial
intelligence, imagine processing, and in
pattern recognition. In the 1970s, It
became more of a science and some
traditional areas of applied mathematics
began to be brought in to, to, to bear on
the problem. And pioneers such has Hann,
Condrain, Klong, and Higgins tried to
understand the, the basic principles of
shape from shading or structure from
motion, and so on. The 1980s, we saw a
vision develo ped as a branch of applied
mathematics. And a variety of different
fields of mathematics were, brought to
bear on vision, including geometry,
multiscale analysis, probabilistic
modeling, control theory, optimization,
and what have you. 1990s were very
successful in the geometric aspect
division. So the basic mathematics of
multiple view geometry was worked out
then, and we started to get the fullest
successful algorithms for recovering 3D
structure. This really flowered in the
2000s in terms of practical applications.
But the basics were all, had all been laid
by the 1990s. Statistical learning
approaches. Which had begun even back in
the 1960's, and the rubric of pattern
recognition really came to the fore in the
1990's, and they had their big successes
in the 2000's. So the 2000's we would call
the age of visual recognition,
it's age that saw major progress.
Recall my earlier example, that on this
Cal Tech [inaudible], performance went up
from sixteen percent correct to 65 percent
correct over a period of three years. And
a number of advances have made this
possible. We have. New machine learning
techniques which have been pretty
effective. We have access to large amounts
of data, large collections of images. Some
estimates range up to a trillion images on
the web, Large collection of video. So we
have a large exam, set of data to work
with. We have the computing power to.
Exploit this data and we have techniques
which, have been developed over the last
ten, twenty years which have enabled us to
make progress on this. So in this course
we'll try to go through the basics of all
these. And, I want to welcome you to the
course and just. In conclusion, tell you
what the main topics we'll study are.
We'll begin with the fundamentals of image
formation, because it's important to
understand both the geometry and
radiometry of image formation. After that,
we'll go through basic image processing
operations, linear filtering, convolution
and so on, because this is the basis for
edge detection and finding boundaries, as
well as the measurement of various image
features which would be useful for recognition.
Then I will go through the
three fundamental R's of vision if you will.
Recognition, we'll spend a lot of
time on that. Recognition of objects,
people, activities, Reconstruction. This
is mainly about recovering 3D geometry,
but we'll also study properties such as
reflectants and so on. And then
reorganization, which is, the grouping of
the image into, sets of pixels
corresponding to different objects. I
hope you enjoy the course and I'll see you
at the next lecture. Bye.