Hello. So, welcome back. In this lecture,
we will talk about Binocular Stereopsis.
So, we previously studied dynamic
perspective. By dynamic perspective, we
meant what happens when the camera moves
and what happens is that we can recover
something some information about depth in
the scene as well as the movement of the
camera. Today, what we will talk about it
the case when we have two static cameras,
But not at the same position. So the
situation described in this diagram, so
it's in this case the setup is
corresponding to the human system. So we
have two eyes, the left eye and the right
eye which are slightly different
locations. We see and object out in the
world through the images created by the
left eye and the image created by the
right eye. And these two images are
slightly different. The difference is
called disparity. That is the technical
term we used for the difference in the
images between the two eyes. And that
disparity is due to depth. So, the way
that you should think about this is that
this is very analogous to optical flow.
So, optical flow was the difference in
position between points in one frame and
the next frame. Disparity is between the
images in one eye versus the image in the
other eye. So disparity is kind the
counterpart of the optical flow. And from
disparity, you should be able to pull out
information which tells us something about
depth in the scene. Why should that be the
case? Well, here's a very simple argument.
Essentially in perspective projection what
we know is that there is a certain ray
going through the pin hole and the point
in the world could lie anywhere on that
ray. You don't know where exactly. Now,
from the second camera, you'll get another
such ray. In this section of these two
rays uniquely defines where the point lies
in three-dimensional space. So this is my
two cameras and label as to c in the left
and that's what the term Stereopsis means.
Stereo means solid and opsis means sight,
so this is solid sight And binocular
implies two eyes. Bi means two and ocular
m eans two eyes. So, two eyes gives
severe, getting solid sight. Now why did
we want to do this case separately from
the case of optical flow? Well, in the
case of the optical flow we derived the
equations using calculus. Essentially the
assumption was the change was that the
small from one frame to next. We don't
need that assumption anymore in this set
of binoculars Stereopsis. The two cameras
could be arbitrary far apart. And we'll
work out formulas which will work in the
general case. [inaudible] The math
simplifies in, in order to give us
formulas for disparity and depth In
different ways depending on the
configuration of the cameras. So, let's
take that up. There can be various camera
configurations or for that matter, eye
configurations. Okay, here is the
configuration corresponding to normal
human vision. We have our two eyes And the
two eyes are fixated at some point In the
world. Okay, Unless you have some disease
or [inaudible] or lazy eye or one of these
problematic-ish diseases. What you
normally do is that left eye and the right
eye are both oriented at the same point we
are concerned, so that's the point that
highest resolution in both left eye and
the right eye. So, this is a very common
configuration for and therefore typical
human and binocular human or animal
vision. So we studied this configuration.
The special case of this when we consider
the fixation point to be it infinitely so
I'll draw it out like so here are the two
eyes. And the optical axis are parallel as
opposed to the optical axis and
intersected. These are a very common
configuration in the camera systems. For
example, in the kinect, you'll have such a
configuration. You have essentially this
configuration with equivalent to, I mean
parallel optical axis And then of course
we can have the general case And general
case the two cameras can be in any
position with respect to another so there
is camera c1. There is camera c2 and in
between what has happened that some
rotation and some transfers. In general
some complete the transformat ion and we
can look out the relationship we want in
that case. But I'd like to start with the
easy case and, and then we'll move on the,
the more complex cases. So first we
studied the dis-clarity for our fixating
binocular system. So here we can just
think of human vision as a good model the
LE standing for the left eye and the right
eye and typically we fixate at some point
B in the world. So the easiest way to see
this is when you are reading then the
letter that you are reading at a
particular point, that's going to be the
point b here, the fixation point. And then
we can have some arbitrary point q. And
this point q is gonna be imaged
differently in the left eye and the right
eye and that difference is what we call
disparity and this disparity is going to
be q to the f. So let's figure this out.
So imagine that we have our coordinate
system in the left eye. Okay. We have an
origin corresponding to the pinhole. We
have a coordinate system in the right eye
and the origin here is going to be on the
optical axis or it's, it's the point p. So
the projection of the point p is at the
origin here in both of these eyes in the
left and the right eye. And therefore its
disparity is zero because it is at the
same position in both eyes. Sometimes, we
use this hard coordinate system called the
Cyclopean Eye. Okay so the Cyclops. Where
these characters from Greek Mythology who
had one eye on top of the head so if we
were to have one eye on our head where
should it be? Logically the right place to
put it is on the midpoint of the line
joining the left eye and the right eye and
we call that the cyclopean eye. I mean
there is no real eye there. It's just
another place to put a coordinate system
which is neutral between being on the left
eye and the right eye. So now we can
consider where our point q is imaged so
the point q is imaged to q sub l in left
eye and q sub r in the right eye. So
what's the definition of disparity?
Disparity is Defined to be q sub r - q sub
l. Now note that qr is a point in
two-dimensional space and ql is also a
point in two-dimensional space so the
disparity has a horizontal component. And
it has a vertical component. Recall that
when we are doing, we were studying
optical flow we had the components u and v
and those were the horizontal component in
the x direction and v the component in the
vertical direction so the same story is
gonna go on here. The main, the component
which is mainly important is the
horizontal component because the eyes are
separated horizontally so the, the
horizontal disparity is the most
significant one. Okay. So, all we do is,
we have got our origins in the left eye
and the right eye. We measure the, the
location of the point q, the projection of
the point q in the two eyes, q sub l, q
sub r. And just take the differences where
ql and qr are measured in the separate
coordinate systems. Okay. Our job now is
going to be to. Measure disparity,
measuring disparity requires finding out
correspondences what point in the left
dimension corresponds ro what point in the
right dimension and we are going to study
that probably later. Today in the next
field of lectures, we are gonna focus
primarily on the geometry of the problem.
Suppose we know the correspondences, how
can we determine that? I want to first
talk a little bit about binocular eye
movements and this a particular interest
in human version because the human eyes
move according to this two basic kind of
eye movements. So the basic set up is the
following. We have the left eye and the
right eye and CE is the cyclopean eye, the
midpoint of left eye and right eye. So I
have my basic set up and I'm fixated on
the point B. Now what I could do is I
could stay looking in the same direction.
Okay? So the cyclopean direction of p has
not changed but just look at the point
which is further away which we call p
prime So what has changed under this
situation in the, under this movement of
the eyes. So basically, I'm still looking
at the same direction but look at the
point further away. So there is an angle
of convergence that we can define if we
have left eye, the point p and the right
eye, we have this angle alpha here. So
what happens when we look further in the
same direction? The angle now becomes beta
and beta is going to be smaller than alpha
And beta would be zero if we look at the
point infinitely far away. So, movements
which only change this angle or
convergence are called vergence movements.
This is the technical term, Vergence. So,
if I keep looking in the same direction
just look nearer farther, I'm going to be
doing a vergence movement. Okay, There is
another movement that we can have where
which corresponds to us looking in
different directions and this is called
the [inaudible] movement. This corresponds
to changing the gaze direction. What do I
mean by gaze direction? Okay again, we
have our left eye, we have the right eye,
the cyclopean eye, the gaze angle is shown
here by this gamma. Gamma is the gaze
angle. So, there is a straight ahead
direction and then there is the angle that
the optical axis makes of the cyclopean
eye makes with respect to that angle which
we'll call gaze angle. So if I'm looking
straight ahead, the gazes angle is zero.
If I'm looking a little bit off to one
side then the gaze angle will be the value
shown here. Okay so vision movement
corresponds to changing the gaze angle but
keeping the angle of convergence the same.
Okay. But that implies the second
geometrical relationship. So what I'm
gonna do is, I have my left eye and the
right eye and I will change the point of
fixation. So, the point of fixation could
be q1 or q2 or q2 and the condition is
that I'm keeping this angle constant so
therefore are always the same theta. Okay,
now we bring in a fact from high school
geometry which is that under this
condition, the locus of the point's q is a
circle. So, this is a beautiful fact. So,
if I consider the left eye and the right
eye and the point of fixation. Then These
three points define a circle and other
points such as Q2 and Q3 they will subtle
the same angle theta. So this is a
property of circles so f or a circle
supposed we have a card defined by left
eye and right eye and then the angles have
attended of Q1 or Q2 or Q3 is always going
to be the same. That's this angle shown
here. So if I keep the angle the of
convergence the same then the fixation
point is essentially going to move on the
circle and we give a name to the circle,
and the circle is called the [inaudible]
circle. This is named after to researchers
from a couple of centuries ago so the
[inaudible] circle is an important
geometrical entity for us to consider.
Here is a observation. The disparity is
zero on the virtual circuit. Okay. Now I
just need to take you to this, this, this
analysis. First of all, what is the
virtual circuit? So, let's get our
notation changed. We have the left eye, we
have the right eye And we have p which is
the point of fixation. So, okay? So far,
so good And this is going to be the origin
of the coordinate system in each of the
eyes. Okay next, what we have is some
general point p prime. Okay Now this
point, p prime could be anywhere I mean
Let us pick a point p prime which happens
to be on the [inaudible] circle. What we
will show is that this point will have
disparity zero. How do we do that? Okay.
So we have to do a little bit of geometry.
So we have the point B, we have the point
B prime so let's look at, first it's good
to see what the, the definitions of
disparity out. So in the left eye we have
the point BL And the point er is the
projection in the right eye. So, these are
the origins of the coordinate systems.
Okay so BL, B by definition has zero
disparity so B has. Zero disparity. It's
the fixation point and it's the origin in
both the left eye and the right eye, okay.
Then, we have the point p prime. And
that's what we are trying to figure out
what's its disparity is. So, p prime
projects to the r prime in the right eye
and pr prime in the left eye And actually,
what I have to do is to measure this
displacement which I am sure [inaudible]
by alpha. I can measure it in pixels or I
can measure it in angles and here I'm
gonna do within angles. So, in this
diagram, these are asserted to be equal.
That they are both alpha but we have to
prove that. Prove. That. Pl and p prime l
this angle is the same as between pr and
pr prime, we have to show this. How do we
do this? Okay. So let's consider this
triangles here. So, these two angles are
equal by the property that we are looking
at the [inaudible] circle. So since it's a
circle and there's a court, these angle
thetas are equal. These angles are equal
again, standard fact of geometry. If these
two angles are equal then, then the
angles. Here and here must also be equal
cuz these are two triangles and if two
angles are equal, then the third angle
must also be equal. If these angles are
equal, then so must these angles be equal.
Okay, and if we call this angle alpha, we
must call the other angle, alpha. So, So
that B, so look at BR, BR prime and that
is going through the right eye. The angle
between them have asserted is equal to the
angle between BL left eye and BL prime
because both of these angles are equal
over there so therefore they must be equal
over here. So, so therefore, we can say
that p, if pl prime is displaced by an
angle alpha, pr is, p prime r is also
displaced by an angle alpha. So, therefore
the disparity is. So, what is disparity?
So we are to compute b prime r - b prime l
which is alpha - alpha which is going to
be zero. So we just shown the disparity of
b prime as zero and what was the property
of b prime that we use for this
calculation that it lies on the
[inaudible] circle? So for all the points
in the [inaudible] circle, the disparity
is zero. So this is a one way to
characterized the [inaudible] circle.
Let's now take up the case of a point
which is not on the [inaudible] circle.
That's where we expect something
interesting. So, what we're gonna do is to
derive a relationship between the
disparity and the depth. So let's do that
so we have here the left eye and the right
eye. I could consider any object here
point B prime but to make this calculatio
n simple I'm going to consider a B prime
which happens to be in the same direction
as B just either further or nearer. Okay.
The distance between the eyes between left
eye and right eye this distance is B. We
use this term a lot. B stands for
baseline. It's a term often used and when
we talked about stereopsis and baseline is
the distance between the two camera
centers and generally if you have a larger
baseline, you are more, you are more
information for doing and construction
stereo depths. Okay. So, we're gonna have
to do some, a little geometry here. So, so
consider the point b left eye, point b and
then this z axis. So, we have this angle
theta and what must be true of, of theta.
Tangent of theta Is equal to b up on to
which is half the baseline that is the
distance here, divided by z. Okay. Now,
consider the point p prime. Okay. Now, p
prime is further out so the angle of
convergence is, or this half angle is
theta minus delta theta. I'm doing that to
make delta theta positive because this is
gonna be a smaller angle. So the tangent
of theta minus delta theta is again b up
on two which is this half baseline. And
then what's the, the base of this, this
triangle, it is z + delta z. Okay. So
that's, that's just a straight forward
observation and now we'll have to do a
little bit of manipulation and what we
want really is a relationship between
disparity which is going to be actually
two delta theta. And the depth which is
going to be delta z Okay? So, we'll make
the standards small angle approximation
that tangent of theta is approximately the
same as theta. So, tan theta is equals b
upon two divided by z will give me this
formula. Delta - theta and again replacing
tan theta, what theta I get to this
formula. And then I just take the
difference here between these two guys.
That will give me the expression shown
here. And if you'll do the algebra, you
will find that delta theta is b * delta z
up on 2z squared. Now, what's the
disparity? The disparity is two delta
theta, why is that so? Well to look here
carefu lly, so there's pl and then pl
prime is p, p prime in the left eye is
displaced slightly by delta theta. And,
what happens in the right eye? It's
displaced again but in the opposite
direction. B prime r is in the opposite
direction to what it was in the left eye
so therefore the difference is actually
for you to consider one of them will have
negative sign so that the difference that
you're to consider which is always going
to be by, the disparity has to be defined
as. P prim r - p prime l, that's the
definition of disparity. So that's gonna
give me two times delta data. So what does
that give? So the disparity is two times
this expression. So the two in the
denominator disappears and we get this
very nice formula. The disparities
baseline b. * delta z up on z squared. So
what will a system do? A system will
typically try to find corresponding
points, from corresponding points you'll
compare the disparity And from that, you
can, you can estimate the delta z which is
the change in depth with respect to the
fixation point. Let's end here for now.