Hello. Welcome back. So, in the last
lecture, we talked about various
configurations for stereopsis, Various
configurations in which the two cameras
could be arranged And we started the
Geometry for these different situations.
So, one of those was when we have a single
point of fixation. With the optical axis
into set this is what happens in human
vision where the two eyes can merge on a
fixation point. Or you can have this
special case where the optical axis are
parallel so this is the case for example
in the connect system where you have two
cameras arranged with optical axis
parallel And finally, we are done to the
general case and where the two cameras
correlated by arbitrary rotation and
translation. So, the focus of this lecture
will be on, on the geometry of that case
and how we can recover three-dimensional
structure in that setting. So, let's study
the general situation and the general
situation we have, what is, is described
as Epipolar Geometry. There's a point m in
the world and that projects to m1 and the
first camera on m2 and the second camera
And the camera's two coordinate frame is
related to that of the first camera by
some general rotation and translation.
What makes it challenging is that we may
not know that rotation and translation so
this has to be determined itself. This is
different from the case of say, human
vision or in the case of robotic camera
configuration where we. Get to choose how
to place the cameras and therefore we know
the distance between the cameras and
information about the convergence angle
and so on, which may be known to us from
other sensors. In this case we are talking
about two cameras in general position with
unknown rotation and translation. So,
therefore The problem that we have is that
we have some set of points out in the
world and we must find corresponding
points but that don't mean points that are
some points in the world and it has a
projection in the left image in the right
image and we know which these two points
correspond to exactly the same scene poin
T. We have given n point correspondences.
We need to recover the depth of those end
points and in addition, recover the
relationship between the camera which is
given by rotation and translation. So
let's first study when this kind of a case
arises. This is the most general case but
we should vary about whether this is two
arbitrary general case or does this
actually arise in practical applications.
And the answer is that it does. So,
standard example is reconstructing
three-dimensional object given for this.
So you may have downloaded this
photographs from the Internet such as from
Flicker or some other website and this
photographs could have been taken by
different people at different times And
The question is can we use those
photographs together to recover the
three-dimensional structure of the object
being used And this can actually be done
and that's why we are going to study this
situation in detail. Before we proceed
further I want to point you to some
example of work in this direction and this
is what in a joint project from the
University of Washington and Microsoft
Research and there are number of links
that are provided here. Before you proceed
with the rest of the lecture, I need you
to pause this lecture, go and check out
these websites, look at the demos, look at
the reconstructions. I think that will set
you up much better for our, [inaudible]
the rest of this lecture is. Okay, so I
assume you intend looked at those
reconstructions and I'm very curious to
know how exactly this is done. So, let's
get into the details. I'm going to give
you the big picture. We will not have time
to understand all the details that is,
that is resolved up here of the research
and I want to make sure you get the big
idea. So basic module in, in this
algorithms is that recovering 3D structure
from two views. So, with the so called
relative orientation, the rotation and
translation which is like the two cameras
being unknown. How do we do this? There
are several steps here. I think I will
give you the big picture first. So, the
first step is that we must find. In
corresponding points in two views so
this requires an algorithm and we will
study those later in the course. For now,
suppose that magically somebody tells you
here are end points in the first camera
and he corresponding end points in the
second camera, these are given to you.
Let's assume we have that. Then, what we
do is we estimate. Something called E
matrix, E for essential. It's very related
to a popular geometry and this matrix is
the following. Remember the skew-symmetrix
matrix associated with a vector and
remember that when we have, do you want to
construct across product with the vector,
there is a certain matrix we construct
which is the skew-symmetrix matrix that is
this hat remember? So we can construct
such a skew-symmetrix matrix corresponding
to the translation vector multiply that
[inaudible] multiply that by R the rotation.
And that gives you a matrix E. It turns
out that using point correspondences we
can estimate E. I have to show you how and
why this idea works. Once we know E, then.
We have to kind of factorize e in some way
and by factorizing E we can recover R and
T, the rotation and the translation which
relates the cameras. Once we have the
rotation and the translation, now the job
is kind of done because the relationship
between the two cameras is known now all
we have to do is recover depth by
triangulation because we have the ray in
each of the cameras. We extend the rays
out in space, the two rays should
intersect. Where they intersect is where
the point leaves in the wall. Now, note
that the job is actually more complicated
because we don't just have two cameras. We
may have hundreds of cameras or thousands
of cameras because I think if some tourist
sites that are thousands of tourists
mailing about it and pictures of the same
site. And we want to use the information
from all the photographs. So, there has to
be an outer loop which combines
information from multiple cameras and
multiple points. Note that all the points
will not be seen by the cameras so there
might be some subset of points which are
seen by cameras one and two So, different
subset in by cameras three and so forth.
The algorithm which is used a the stages
so called nonlinear least-squares
optimization procedure called bundle
adjustment. And in any nonlinear least-squares
minimization there is some objective
function that we wished to minimize and
the objective function here is the so
called reprojection error. I'm going to
explain this idea in the subsequent slide.
Just to give you an idea of complexity of
this task, there, I referred in the
previous slide to the University of
Washington and Microsoft Research. They
have a reconstruction of the coliseum in
Rome and this reconstruction was based on
2,000 images, so 2,000 different camera
photographs were taken and there were
800,000 points Which we'll use to
construct this part of the
reconstruction. So there's a significant
engineering problem of how to do this
non-linear optimization but we will let
you skip those details. So let's try to
understand these basic steps first. The
one, the basic inner loop in which
is the covering 3d structures from two
views. Okay. So this is the essential
matrix constraint. And the essential
matrix is defined as a take the skew-symmetric
matrix corresponding to translation And
post to multiply that by R the
rotation matrix. So why does this work?
Okay, I'm going to have to explain that.
But first let me just Give you the big
picture what the constraint is. So they
called us geometry for, there's epipolar
geometry that we started earlier that at
some point m in the world, there are the
camera centers c1 and c2 and the
projections are given by m1 and m2. So m,
c1, c2 defined a plane and that plane is
the so called epipolar plane and
where  it intersect the image planes are called,
we get two lines and these are the so
called epipolar lines. Okay. So, the big
picture is that there is a constraint
which relates the coordinates x1 and x2 of
the point m1 and the two cameras so let's
understand what each of these. So what is
x1? So x1 is the coordinates of  the
projection of m and the first camera m1.
So this is going to be a 2-dimensional
point, it's on the image plane. How are we
going to consider it in homogeneous
coordinates so then it becomes a 3-vector.
And in homogeneous coordinates, any scale
multiple of that vector is also the same.
It's not affected by scale multiplication.
And if you want you can think of this as
the ray going through c1 and the point m.
And the 3-dimensional coordinates of all
the points on that ray correspond to the
homogeneous coordinates of the projection
of the point m in the first camera and
similarly we get x2 and x2 are the
homogeneous coordinates of the projection
of the point m in the second camera. So we
get this, there is this, This quite
magical formula that I've written out
here. Okay. Can we derive this formula? I
want to give you the basic intuition.
Okay. The proof is based on the fact that
there are three rays which are
[inaudible]. So if you look at the
diagram, I have this highlighted in the
green, in purple and in this light blue
color. And what are these three rays?
Remember we talked about the epipolar
constraint which is that there is a
certain plane called the epipolar plane.
So these three Sides of this triangle if
you [inaudible] obviously planer. So let's
see if we can get some mileage out of
that. So how do we do this? We are going
to have to express this constraint in some
algebraic way. So basically, what we
should do is we need to use a consistent
coordinate system and the coordinate
system that we will use is data of the
second camera frame. Okay. So, index
second camera frame, how do I describe
what are the three rays that I'm concerned
with. One ray is the ray corresponding to
x2 which is essentially the ray
corresponding to the projection of m in
the second camera. Okay. So I know what
that is, that's going to be given by the
image plane coordinates of x2 and of
course any scale multiple of that works
equally well. I have the translation vect
or T and that's another ray. Then we have
the ray corresponding to m1, m1, c1, m So
m1, c1, m That's this guy. Okay, but, and
that has coordinate x1 but that's in the
frame of the first camera. That's not good
enough for me. I really need to put
everything in the frame of the second
camera And what's going on between these
two cameras is that there has been a
rotation r. So therefore, if I want to
take the x1 which is in the coordinate
frame of the first camera and I want to
put it in the coordinate frame of the
second camera, I have to do a rotation. So
that give, that I do by this matrix
multiplication rx1. So that, so by doing
that matrix multiplication, rx1 is now put
in the coordinate frame of the second
camera and I've indicated that here so
this translated this line here and now
it's in the coordinate frame center at c2
and I have this ray rx1. So we get that
x2, t and rx1 are all co-planer. Okay.
It's just the epipolar, the basic
constraint of epipolar geometry. So in my
last lecture, I went to an, at great line
for about epipolar geometry and now I'm
going to use the constraint in an
algebraic way to get an equation out. So
since this three are co-planer, the triple
product is zero now. So now, I think I
need to remind you what the triple product
is. So, triple product is a very standard
concept from vector algebra So if we have
vectors v1, v2 and v3 and if they are
co-planer. Then the following is true
that, that take v2 cross v3, the cross
product of vector product. That's this
guy. And then you take the dot product
with the third vector and that gives you
zero. And physical interpretation of this
is, this is the volume of the parallel of
[inaudible] defined by three sides v1, v2
and v3. And when this three line up plane,
the volume of this parallel of [inaudible]
must be zero. Okay. Now let's put this in
odd notation In odd notation. In our
notation, first we make it into we want to
get use this vector notation and we take
this [inaudible] and we'll convert it into
a scale symmetric matrix and we saw that
before. So, so, we do cross product with
v3, I'm going to convert into a vector
matrix multiplication after making
[inaudible] symmetric matrix. And then I
have to take a dot product here and the
dot product when we have, these guys are
column vectors so if I take the column
vector and I transpose it. I get a row
vector and then this product then will,
this will correspond to, to getting the
inner product of the dot product. Okay, so
this is generic, this has nothing to do at
epipolar geometry [inaudible] vectors v1,
v2 and v3 are co-planer, the relationship
described here must be true. So let's go
back. So we have that the vectors x2, t
and rx1 are co-planer, so therefore we can
setup the triple product and that's what
is done here. So we take x2 transposed.
The [inaudible] symmetric matrix
corresponding to, Corresponding to, to t
shows up here that is rx1 which is like
one guy and this triple product to zero
And then what we do is we give this. It
gives this matrix a name; they call this
the matrix e And it's sometimes called the
essential matrix. It's certainly is very
essential to our understanding of
stereopsis. Okay. Now, we are ready to get
the big picture of the so called
Longuet-Higgins Eight-point algorithm.
This is the famous algorithm. It goes back
to 1981 and was proposed by, by
Longuet-Higgins and was named after him.
So, what we do is we find, we need to have
corresponding points in the two views and
this algorithm requires eight or more
points. From these points, we, we proceed
in the following steps. We, We estimate
the e matrix which is the, this particular
product of d and r. From this, we do some
kind of factorization, I'm going to
[inaudible] the details of that and that
gives me the relationship between the two
cameras, and once I have the relationship
between the two cameras, I can recover
[inaudible]. Let me give you a little bit
more intuition about the step, why this
works and why we need eight points. Okay.
So, let's start with the equation. Given
projections x1, x2 so x1 and x2 are this
is the first camera and this is the second
camera and x1 and x2 will be measured in
each camera's coordinates. And we have
this relationship that it derives in a
previous slide that x2 transpose ex1 is
equal to zero. What do we know here? So
the knows are, x2 is known and x1 is
known, e is unknown. Alright so these guys
e is unknown. Okay. Can we solve for e.
Well e is actually a [inaudible] matrix so
that's. Write this out. So we are now just
expanded out this equation into the
coordinates. So, x2 is a three by one
vector so x2 transpose [inaudible] is a
certain row vector, x1 is a column vector
which is shown here and then in between we
have this three by three matrix e which is
unknown. Okay But if you write out this
equation. And. What we get is an equation
involving the radius entries in e. And
remember that x2 is known and x1 is known.
So this is actually a linear equation
where the unknowns are e11, e12, e13, e21,
e22, e23, e31, e32, e33. So, there are
really nine unknowns here and we have one
linear equation. Now, imagine that you
have a new some other Point for which
you'll get the coordinates in both cameras
that will give you another equation and so
on. So we get every time we find a pair of
corresponding points in the two cameras,
we get a new linear equation involving
this, this nine entries of the e matrix.
There is one observation we can make here,
which is that, we can only recover this e
matrix up to a scale factor. Why is that?
Suppose you took the entries of e And
replaced, suppose we took e and instead of
e we have [inaudible] times e Would this
equation be exactly the same? Yes, there
is no way you can solve for the difference
between e and the scale of multiple of e
And in fact, if you think about this from
a projective geometry point of view, that
is exactly correct because in projective
geometry, these matrix are always known up
to an unknown scale factor, up to an
unknown non-zero scale factor. So in fact,
we can never hope to recover nine
parameters because there's always been
this unknown scale factor. So, we can only
hope to recover eight parameters. Okay and
then there will be this unknown scale
factor. So Then if, then now you know from
linear equation theory that if you have,
if you have five unknowns, you need five
equation, So in this case we have eight
unknowns, so therefore we need eight
equations And how do we get eight
equations? By having eight corresponding
points, So this eight is really the nine
entries of the essential matrix minus one
because we can never hope to recover the
scale factor, So, this algorithm is called
the Eight-point algorithm. The beauty is
that with eight correspondences you can
actually just solve linear equations in
order to recover the entries of this
matrix e If you have more than eight
points, that fine. There are still the
same eight unknowns, more point is better,
we can do some kind of [inaudible] square
solution by which we minimize there so
more results are better and in, when we
are solving linear equation, this is
what's called an OWA determined linear
system and we can always solve for that
and that's good. So That gives you the
intuition of how, how the e matrix comes
about and how we can estimate it, given
[inaudible] correspondences. Once we have
the e matrix, the e matrix in turns out
can be factorized to give us all the
rotational components and to either
translation component and I'm going to
skip the details. It's, can be found in
any of the references in this, on the
literature And once we have that, we can
recover that by [inaudible] So just to
summarize what we studied so far. The
basic module for recovering 3D structure
from 2-views with unknown relative
orientation between the cameras, unknown
rotation and translation can be
implemented using the Longuet-Higgins
eight point algorithm. Of course, we have
a more general situation which is that we
have many cameras and many points and how
do we do that But in a loop is this
Longuet-Higgins eight-point algorithm. The
outer loop combines information from all
the cameras in a global c oordinate system
using what's called bundle adjustment.
The, this is a least [inaudible]
minimization procedure and the important
point here is what error is being
minimized. The error that is minimized is
so called re-projection error. And I'll
give you the intuition here. So, we have
from this Eight-point algorithm, we
essentially have a bunch of approximate
guesses of the position of the cameras and
the position of the point in three space
with the approximate because of the
presence of the image noise and all the
rest. But once we have guessed 3D position
to the point, we can use the equation of
prospective projection to exactly predict
where the point should lie in each of the
cameras whether point is visible And if
the image measurement of the coordinates
of the point is not exactly there then we
have some slide discrepancies and that
discrepancy is what is called the
re-projection error. You guessed where the
point was in 3D, you predicted where it
should be in the image, you look for it
and you found it to be not exactly there
but somewhere nearby and so there's a
little error there. You sum the errors
corresponding to all the predictions for
all the points and all the views. So we
get this humongous error function And what
we do is we try to adjust the position of
the cameras and the points in three space
such that this error is minimized. So
it's, it's not a convex optimization
problem. It's a non-linear problem where
you can only find local minimal. If you
start off close enough to the right point,
this procedure works and it's called
bundle adjustment that's kind of the term
we used, I mean for a mathematician, this
is just non-linear [inaudible] but in
vision and really goes back to [inaudible]
geometry we called this bundle adjustment.
Because [inaudible] adjusted is the bundle
of rays Going through the center of
projection of a particular camera.
Actually, we have lots of bundles
corresponding to all the camera positions.
I have only given you the big picture of
the, the, the, this whole line of w ork.
Lots and lots of engineering where
literally decades has gone into make the,
making this whole approach work and I
welcome you to pursue this further. Good
introduction can be found in Rick
Szeliski's book, Chapter seven and this
book is available free online so you can
download it and read and study it. Thank