Welcome back. We're ready to resume study
of Geometry of Stereopsis and now we are
ready to tackle the general case. So, the
general case, we don't know how the two
cameras are arranged in space and we still
have to figure out what the depths of
points are. And this happens often enough,
like very common scenario is we download
images from the Internet. So for example
these could be many people taking
photographs of Eiffel Tower or any
landmark that you might like and what we
want to do is to generate a 3D model of
the Eiffel tower from this multiple
photographs so. In this case, we do not
know how these photo, where these
photographs were taken from. There is some
unknown Euclidean transformation which
relates these cameras, we don't know that.
What we should be able to do otherwise to
solve for point correspondences among the
images and somehow figure out everything.
Figure out how those two cameras are
arranged in space as well as what the
depths of points are. Of course, the
general problem requires multiple cameras,
not just two. I mean, you have thousands
of tourists taking pictures of the same
object in, in, in some tourist spot. But
we'll currently study the case for two
cameras and the general cases fairly
straight forward. So let's go to it and.
What we have to understand here is the
notion of Epipolar Geometry. So, this is a
multiple but I'll try to take you this
notion in a series of slides. So, I have
this basic diagram that I want you to try
to understand and get a good physical
inclusion for. So, we have some point
amendable and it is imaged in two cameras.
The two cameras have camera center c1 for
the first camera and c2 for the second
camera. I could say first the camera, the
second camera or I could say left camera
and right camera. Pretty soon that left
and right camera will seems to be
meaningful because it could be the left
camera just above the right camera and so
on but let's say that this notation for
now. I want you to get a sense of a
physical picture here. So C1 here is the
pin hole an d then we have the image plate
and where is the image plate? The image
plate is f units Behind c1. So, c1 is in
front of the image plane. So, please don't
make the mistake of assuming that c1 lies
in the image plane. C1 does not lie in the
image plane, c1 is the pinhole, c1 is the
center of projection. C1 is in front of
the left camera. Similarly, c2 is in front
of the right camera. It's in, it's in
front by distances of f. It's not lying on
the image plane of the camera. Okay. So
now this diagram illustrates how image
projection happens so we have M which is
the point in the world. C1 does inter
projection so we can draw the line between
M and C1 The real Going through C1 from M
and that way intersects the image plane
from camera one at some point and let's
call that point M1. Similarly the ray from
M through C2 intersects camera two at the
point ends at two so ends at two is the
projection. So M1 and M2 do lie on the
image planes of the respective cameras but
C1 and C2 are in fact by distance of F, So
far so good. What I'm gonna take you
through is the definition of Epipolar
plane. Okay. It's a fairly straight
forward definition bit it will give us a
lot of image so it's what's understanding
[inaudible] detail. If there's a point m
in the world, consider the plane formed by
m, c1 and c2. So, it's a point in the
world and the two cameras, center of
projection, m, c1, c2. So, this is a plane
and here it is shown by this, this dash
lines and this [inaudible] plane, we call
the Epipolar plane. Okay. Note that we can
describe it as MC1C2 but I could also
describe it as MM1, the projection of, of
the point M in camera one or And then n2
which is the projection of MA camera two.
So if I consider m, m1, m2, that is the
same plane. In fact, this is gonna be
important because we are eventually going
to make observations just from images.
Those tourists have uploaded those
photographs and now we have only access to
those photographs. So, that's the concept
of Epipolar plane. Now there can be many
Epipolar planes because we can have
different points and we could choose the
point on a new point m which does not lies
on this Epipolar plane in which case we'll
get a new Epipolar plane. Sometimes people
use Book of Epipolar Planes because why,
why is it a book? Well consider, think of
c1, c2 as being the spine of this book and
the entire fact, all the Epipolar Planes.
Go through the lines C1, C2 but it's like
a book where there is spine of the book,
the spine of the book would be C1, C2 and
then we have all the sheets of the book.
Okay so we now understand the notion of
Epipolar plane. The next important idea is
of Epipolar line. Epipolar lines are the
intersections of the Epipolar plane with
the image planes. So we have our Epipolar
plane, Mc1, c2. It will intersect the
image plane of the left camera on some
line. Okay. So that line is shown here in
red and we call that an Epipolar line on
the left camera or on the first camera
depending on what you like. And then, the
same plane, Mc1, c2 intersects the image
plane of the right camera on some other
line and that shown here and that's.
Called the Epipolar line in the second
camera so we have one Epipolar plane in
C1, C2 and it gives rise to two Epipolar
lines One in the left camera, one in the
right camera. Okay. So now I have explicit
mark these so we have the Epipolar line in
the left camera, the Epipolar line in the
right camera. The big observation here is
that the projection of M in the post
camera which I will call M1 and the
projection o M in the second camera which
is M2. M1 and m2 lay on corresponding
Epipolar lines. So, this Epipolar lines
come in pairs because once that we defined
that Epipolar plane, we get the two
Epipolar lines which corresponds to the
intersection with the two image planes And
the projection of this, all the points in
this Epipolar plane and then many of them.
It's not just the point m but any point
which lies on this Epipolar plane is going
to project to the. In the left camera to
the corresponding Epipolar line and in the
right camera to the other c orresponding
Epipolar, Epipolar line, So, note that
there are some situations in which this
Geometry is very simple. So, suppose the
two cameras are arranged with their
optical axis parallel to each other, we
started this case; this corresponds to
looking at infinity. It parallel optical
axis. In this case, Epipolar, The Epipolar
Geometry is particularly simple. All the
Epipolar lines are horizontal lines so
that's a very simple case. But the theory
I have described in the last few slides is
the general theory and this applies to any
two cameras. They are not required to have
intersecting optical axis or parallel
optical axis or whatever. This will always
be true for any two cameras because two
cameras will have optical center c1, c2,
pick a point out in the wall called M.
Mc1, c2 defines the Epipolar plane, the
intersection is defined the Epipolar
lines. There is one other term I want you
to keep in mind. This is the so called
Epipol. Epipol is, there is an Epipol in
each, in each camera and Epipol is the
projection of the Pinhole of the other
camera. So, what is Epipolar e1? E1 is,
let's state a point c2 which is the center
of projection of the second camera and
let's figure out where c2 projects in the
camera and that is call the e1. So,
essentially, we consider the ray from c2
to c1 and then we extend that. And then,
it will intersect the image plane and that
point is e sub one and that's called the
Epipolar in the left camera. That's just
the terminology and the double b, that
take that same line c1, c2 and now
projected to intersect. The second image
plane, the right camera's image plane and
there that intersection point we will call
e sub two and that's the Epipole in the
right camera. Okay, so now we have added
one more term to our vocabulary. We have
Epipolar plane, Epipolar lines and
Epipoles. Okay so why are we doing all
these? We're doing all these because we
want to deal with the case of images taken
back to cameras which are with some
unknown position with respect to each
other. By unknown positi on I mean there
could be some rotation which and
translation which relates the camera to
its coordinate frame to that of camera
one. And we don't know it, it's some
unknown odd and some unknown [inaudible]
and what we have access to other images
are each of these cameras. So that's going
to be the, the general version of the
synopsis problem. We have given. Some n
image points in the left camera and in the
right camera. And we do not know the
relationship between the coordinate frames
of the two cameras. So, we were given end
points correspondences. We do know that,
that for this end points, we know what
that partners are. We know that there is a
point a in the left image and this end
point a prime in the right image, they
both correspond to the same point out in
the world. So, we have given these end
point correspondences and our goal is to
estimate the rotation and translation
which derives the cameras And the depths
of the n points so we'll take that up
later. Thank you.