Hello Welcome back. So, we're gonna
continue with our analysis of the Geometry
of Binocular Stereopsis. In the previous
lecture, I talked about The camera
configuration where we had fixation
geometry high. The optical axis of the two
cameras intersect and this is typically
the case and say human vision where the
two eyes converge on the same point. Now
we move on to more general geometries and
this one which is very common in the
design of robot vision assistance which is
to keep the two camera optical axis
parallel to each other so this is You can
think of it as a special case of the
previous one is just the fixation point is
infinity And then of course, there's the
more general case for the optical axis,
they don't intersect at all. So, I'm going
to, for the next few slides focus on the
case of optical axis parallel and cut the
geometry of the relationship between
disparity and depth in the setting. Okay
so this would require a little bit of
geometry so let's try to keep everything
straight. So we have two cameras denoted
here by the left eye and the right eye. So
left eye is the camera's optical center
for one camera and re stands for the right
eye, Meaning, the optical center of the
other camera And ce is always is the
cyclopean eye, the eye which is at the
midpoint of the optical centers of the
left and right eye And the coordinate
system for the c is centered from the
Cyclops e and I And in this coordinate
system, we have an x axis and we have a z
axis Z axis going into depth and x axis as
shown here. Okay. So, now what we are
going to do is to figure where a point p
in the world project in the two images. So
we have f, the focal length has before,
Standard Notation for Perspective
Projection and b stands for the baseline.
Baseline is the horizontal distance
between the left eye and the right eye
center. So, that's b To not it here, I
could measure b between left eye and right
eye Horizontal displacement. Okay, So if
we have a point p then, let's consider
where it projects in the, in the left eye.
So in th e left eye, the ray must go
through to the, the, the, the optic the
center of projection or the pinhole and
then the image is produced at the point
shown here and then the location of that
marked as x of l. In the right eye, we
again have a point b projecting to the
location xr, x of r in this case And the
ray must go through the pin hole indicated
here. Okay. Let's figure it out the
geometry and essentially we have to do
similar triangles. It's the same kind of
story that we have seen before when we
were trying to understand prospected
projection with one camera. So the only
ticket in there is that there are a couple
of different coordinate systems involved
and then we need to talk about upper case
X, Y, and Z For the point b. So the point
b is upper case X, upper case Y, upper
case Z and this is with respect to the
Cyclopean Eye. So that's the right place
to put the coordinate system because we
can't choose left or right. We can't favor
one of them so let's put the coordinate
system right there average at the center
of the two. Okay. So then the coordinate
system will be as shown here. This is the,
the origin is at the cyclopean eye that is
the x axis of the cyclopean eye, the z
axis of the cyclopean eye And now we have
to consider these similar triangles. So
there is one similar triangle which is
essentially going to be. This triangle was
as the triangle here. And what can I see
there? So we're going to get x of l / f,
okay? That expression you see here is the
ratio of the base to the high rate And
Then we have to consider the ratio of this
distance. To Z now this distance here to
do a little bit of thinking and figure out
why this is upper case X + b upon two and
b is the baseline and essentially it's
because the origin that shifted by a
distance by b upon two, b / two and so
there's, that's just the shift of, caused
by the shift of origin. Xr up on f is
going to be X - b / two up on z so that's
we will get for the point xr. And here we
have a different set of similar, similar
triangles that we have to consi der. So,
to make sense of these formulas we are
taking to account that x is a signed
quantity. Okay. Once we have these
expressions, life is actually quite
simple. So, we, what is this, parity. This
parity is going to be xl minus xr. And
what is that going to be? That's going to
be to take to take the difference of these
two expressions and that's going to give
me b / z and of course it's not xl or xr
but really xl up on f - xr up on f. So
therefore we get the formula the
dis-parity which is xl minus xr. It's b
time's f upon c. So I would summarize this
formula here where I got rid of, much of
this clutter. So in the case of parallel
optical axis F is the focal length of each
of the two cameras. D is the baseline, the
distance between the left eye and the
right eye and the point b is somewhere,
the disparity so Excel is the coordinate
of the point b in the left eye. Xr is the
coordinate to the point in the right eye.
And in the dis-parity xl minus xr is
simply given by b times f upon c. So, from
this formula you again see the usual
thing. If the baseline is longer, you have
the cameras for their apart then you get a
greater disparity. I mean obviously that
should be the case because that the real
case is gonna baseline zero then you
should get known your information and
obviously dis-parity then is zero And then
the dis-parity for [inaudible]. So, what
that does mean? That means that as he goes
to infinity. The disparity here is zero.
So that should be the case, we call it the
Parallel Optical Axis and at infinity, the
point should project the same location in
both eyes so that should be no disparity.
Okay. So note that to apply these
formulas, we need to know about
correspondence so this is a big idea.
Correspondents, Correspondence means that
I need to know for the point p, there's a
point p in the wall. And it projects to a
point p sub l in the left eye and p sub r
in the right eye. And I need to figure
this correspondent out that such as that
image location on one eye correspond to
such as that image locatio n that I got.
And this is the take considerable work
mostly to the work and stereopsis
algorithm is about solving the
correspondence problem. There are settings
how on which the correspondence problem is
made really easy with the use of active
sensing. So, there are. This is on the
case of so-called range sensors. So, the
range sensors use extra hardware not just
cameras and use some active device to
project Electromagnetic radiation into
the, the scene. It could be lightning, it
could be a laser, it could be an infrared
beam, whatever. And, these made the
correspondence problem very easy. So I'll
gonna show you two examples of ray sense.
One is the so called prime sense which is
used in the Kinect system and many of you
may have played with these. So, the, the,
in the Kinect senses what happens is that
you have essentially a triangle device.
There is an active. Projection of an
infrared beam into the scene and then that
is image. By an, by an IR camera And
infrared camera And we'll see later that
this give rise to certain geometry which
corresponds to the case of Parallel
Optical Axis. At the same time you also
have an RGB camera to take an ordinary
image of the scene. So this is the so
called triangle relation base device. You
can also have Dynaflite senses. So
Dynaflite senses Very simple. You have
essentially something like a laser being
shot into the world. Then it comes back
and the speed of light is finite. So, you
can measure the amount of time it took and
by that you can calculate the distance. So
there are many devices on the market base
on either simulation principles or time of
flight principles and these devices enable
one to directly measure depth values in
the scene so you can actually get
measurements of z at many different
locations on the scene. So, these, these
have been used for automatic card driving
and video games and all the rest. Let me
talk a little bit more about the Kinect
type senses which you get there from
triangulation and I want to compare. The
case of passive stereopsis with act ive
stereopsis, So, passive stereopsis is what
we just looked out the formula for. Here
are two cameras, camera one and camera
two. Their optical axis are parallel and
they actually got this nice formula that
the disparity is b * f up on z. Okay. So
here we have a light originates from
points in the wall and then it comes to
each of the two cameras. So these are
passive devices, the cameras themselves do
not emit any energy. [inaudible] When you
have a Kinect type device, you'll have an
active system. There is some projector of
light into the scene, some pattern into
the scene and then that pattern is imaged
in the camera. So, the, if you notice the
arrows here, there is some energy being
emitted into the scene, projected into the
scene. But notice that the geometry is
exactly the same. Right There are, the
directions of the raise maybe different
but consider as lines they cause, they're
exactly the same geometry. The main
advantage of active sensing is that it
simplifies the problem of estimating point
correspondences. So if I have projected
particularly point and seeing it's a
bright spot I just see, where is that
bright spot image in my camera? I don't
have to solve for the search for the
correspondents by doing some kind of
search and so on. So, it does make the
correspondence problem much easier but. At
the expense of requiring this active
projection of energy and seeing which
means that it's gonna cost a little bit
more and they sent an application where we
may want to be detected or project energy
into a scene and so on and so forth. So
let's do a little bit of the analysis of
the accuracy a triangle relation based
censor, given that we've the already done
the hard work for straight system based on
triangulation. So, we call the formula for
disparity with parallel optical axis.
Formula for the disparity is xr-xr is bf
upon z. So, in other words, you can say
disparity is some constant. Upon z. Okay,
that's gonna be the case or I could say it
at some other way; z is some other
constant upon depth, okay? Kee p this
relation in mind and we'll look at the,
the a formula for the accuracy of depth
estimation. Okay. So we, we can try to
understand what's the error as a function
of this transform Kinect type sensor. And
we can do this purely from geometrical
analysis. So we recall the, the
relationship between this transcend and
disparity and that relationship is what I
showed you in the previous slide. So
there's, it doesn't matter what the
constant is this, some constant, but the
important point is there an invoice
relationship that c is proportional to one
up on the disparity. Okay. So now we can
do calculus. So if I have a little error
in the measurement of disparity, what does
it translate to in terms of an error in
estimating that? So we can do calculus, we
can take the derivatives off z with
respect to d and do a little bit of
manipulation and you can try it yourself.
We should, we can see that delta z is - z
squared up on z * delta d. So, now we can
take absolute magnitude here since we are
trying to concern with errors and we get
the following formula That the area delta
z is related to the area delta d in the
disparity measurement With this
multiplicative factor which is z squared.
So, that's says that the area is
proportional to distance squared. So, this
give us the prediction that if I am
making, using the kinect for depth
measurement one meter away, I'll have,
let's say some error But if I'm looking at
points which are ten meters away. Then,
the, the error will go up by not a fact of
ten but actually a fact of hundred. So one
of my students actually made measurements
with the Kinect sensor and those
measurements here are shown with these
blue, this deep blue dots where what he
did was he, for varying distances in the
scene, he tried to measure what the
quantization that are off the output from
the Kinect was and those are these little
blue dots. And. The red cove here is the
quadratic figure that comes from this
formula because that we know that the
dependents theoretically should be b
squared. And note that the blue dots lie
exactly on top of this red curve which
shows that once in a while geometry does
have predicted bar. Thank you.